<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bountiful Money Coaching</title>
    <description>Save money, budget according to your values, and experience financial bliss</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Credit Card Float</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a hidden debt trap that you could be falling into. I know I sound like one of those terrible commercials trying to persuade you to give them money to get your debt cancelled. But there &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; a way to get into debt without knowing you are in debt, and it is called “Credit Card Float.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit Card Float is where you charge your everyday expenses to your credit card over the period of the month, then when you get paid, you pay off the credit card in full, thus never incurring any interest payments. The trouble is, you don’t have enough money to pay for your upcoming expenses, so you have to turn right around and start using the credit card again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the simple way to tell if you are Floating. Ask yourself “If I paid off my credit card today, would I have enough money to cover my expenses until the next time I get paid?” If you answer no, then you are Floating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are in debt because you are paying for expenses first, then getting your income to cover those expenses later. It means that if for some reason you became unemployed, or stopped making money, you would already be one month of expenses in debt, with no way to pay it off. What a scary place to be! Just when you need full reserves, you’ll find yourself in debt before you can even think about how to get out of your current income crunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;YNAB&lt;/a&gt;, my favorite budgeting program, one of the four rules used to be “Live on Last Month’s Income”. I will write about that rule sometime in the future, but basically the idea is you are always running one month ahead of your expenses. When you are Floating, you are doing the opposite, you are paying for today’s expenses with &lt;strong&gt;next&lt;/strong&gt; month’s income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-you-get-out-of-credit-card-float&quot;&gt;How do you get out of Credit Card Float?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to get out of the Credit Card Float. But here are a few ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stop&quot;&gt;Stop!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above all, stop using your credit card, and start using your debit card. This separates your ongoing spending from your Float (debt), which makes it easier to use any one of the following methods to pay off the Float. Note that when you switch to the debit card, you will not be able to pay off your credit card in full next month, because you were using that money to pay this month’s expenses, which will mean you will start incurring interest charges. Usually Float isn’t a huge amount, as it is equal to one month’s expenses, so if you prioritize paying of your Float, you’ll be able to get rid of it quickly, and probably have spent very little on interest in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to keep paying at least the minimum payment, though! You don’t want to harm your credit while you’re paying down this debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-your-savings&quot;&gt;Use your savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky enough to have some savings, you can pull some of those savings out, and pay off your credit card bill with that, instead of next month’s paycheck. This is probably the quickest and cheapest way to get current with your credit card. It can hurt emotionally to use your savings to pay the Float, but remember, your savings is already a bit illusory, because you are also in debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;throw-your-extra-cash-into-it&quot;&gt;Throw your extra cash into it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a windfall, sell something, or get a gift, throw that money at your credit card. Every little bit helps, and eventually, you will pay off your Float.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-your-extra-paycheck&quot;&gt;Use your extra paycheck.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you get paid every two weeks? If so, every year you have two months where you get paid three times a month, instead of two. If one of those months is coming up, consider using the “extra” paycheck to throw at your Float. It can bring your balance down by at least half, which is a huge morale boost, then you can work on the rest of the balance using other methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few ideas for paying it down. Like all debt payment strategies, the most important thing is to get creative! Make it a game – how quickly can you pay down your Float?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve paid off your Float, you can consider starting to use your credit card again. Because you already have a proven track record of paying your credit card off every month, you’ll probably continue to do well with it. But now when you use it, every dollar you spend on your credit card, you know you have a dollar in your bank account that backs that debt. It’s an amazing feeling to know that you can pay your credit card at any time, and still have enough money in your account to pay for all your expenses!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/06/Credit-Card-Float.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/06/Credit-Card-Float.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Balance Giving with Budgeting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When we explore our money life, we dig deep into our bills, essentials like groceries, debt payments, and discretionary spending. But today I’d like to focus on one kind of spending that can cause a wide range of emotional reactions, especially during the holiday season: Giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving needs to be explored at a personal finance level because generosity is an important aspect of most people’s lives. I have found in my time as a Money Coach, there are clients that are willing to reduce expenses in a wide variety of areas in their lives, but will flat out refuse to eliminate or reduce their giving. And I understand that! Giving can be tied into who we are as people. We identify with the causes we give to, and it can feel miserly to stop or reduce giving. So let’s examine how giving can fit into our life, now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-personal-history-with-giving&quot;&gt;My personal history with giving&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently took a class from my mentor Luna Jaffe called &lt;a href=&quot;http://lunajaffe.com/wild-money/&quot;&gt;Wild Money&lt;/a&gt;. In this class she talked about six different aspects of personal finance: Receiving, Spending, Nurturing, Growing, Protecting, and Giving. I struggled more with the Giving section than I did with the other five sections &lt;strong&gt;combined&lt;/strong&gt;. I had some angry reactions to talking about generosity and giving. That in turn made me feel guilty and like I was a bad person. It turns out I’m and under-giver (more on under- and over-giving later) which means I don’t give as much as my life situation could allow, and I don’t give as much as I would like to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is that? In the Wild Money class, we explored various reasons why I could be struggling so much with giving. Not until the very end of class did I realize that I have a couple of deep family dynamics that have conspired to make giving a difficult subject. My mother was, towards the end of her life, a very needy person. She would take from me, emotionally and financially, without regard for my ability to give, and I finally had to put some very firm boundaries between her and me in order to maintain my sanity. This led me to have some pretty complex feelings about what it means to give to people, especially those that need a lot of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another dynamic I discovered is my family has a history of strings-attached giving. Again, this makes it hard for me to understand how a healthy, freely given gift looks and works. I have by no means fully worked through these issues, but just knowing they exist makes me realize I’m not just a bad person for my under-giving behaviors. And it gives me a basis to heal my relationship with giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself, how was giving modeled in your family? Have you had times where giving was not healthy in your life? Do you connect giving with manipulation, as I do? Or does it stem from guilt or other negative feelings? Understanding your history can help you progress to a healthy relationship with giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-in-balance&quot;&gt;Giving in balance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you continue to give, while healing your own financial situation? Like many things, I ascribe to the mantra of &lt;em&gt;balance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, let’s say you work for a non-profit, collecting donations for a cause you believe in. Every month, a woman comes in, and writes you a check for $500 dollars. It’s a generous gift, and you are always delighted to see her. One day, you notice she’s outside, arguing with a younger man, who walks away as she comes inside. As she opens her checkbook, she says, “my son is always trying to tell me what to do. He says I’m getting myself into debt because of this. But I don’t care, this cause is too important to stop.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would this make you feel? Would you feel good that she is overextending herself in order to give to your cause? Or would you be sad that she is spending beyond her means, causing her and her family distress and strife?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably would want her to stop overextending herself, even though you yourself believe so strongly in your cause. Turn that back on yourself – do you give so much of yourself that you have nothing left for yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-from-abundance&quot;&gt;Giving from abundance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually only recommend reducing your giving spending when your life is particularly out of balance: you either have far too little income to support your giving, or your giving is causing you to go into debt. You may have objections to reducing giving spending, but I want you to consider two things. The first is that this is only a temporary measure. The second is that we want to reduce your spending now so you can get your situation stable, so that you can spend more on giving later. When you are able to give from a place of abundance, you can give freely, and the gifts can do more good than if you are giving from a place of scarcity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-creatively&quot;&gt;Giving creatively&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, if you need to reduce your giving, what should you do? You can continue to give while you are financially stretched, but it must be done creatively. You can give in various ways, but the two most common are: giving money, and giving time. If you are reducing your spending, then volunteering your time can be a rewarding way of giving of yourself. In fact, you may find that you like the hands-on nature of giving like this. You can dig into the details of causes that interest you, and find real reward by giving your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-kind-of-giver-are-you&quot;&gt;What Kind of Giver Are You?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-give-beyond-your-means&quot;&gt;You give beyond your means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you give beyond your means, it makes it harder to take care of yourself, which means it is going to be harder to give to others later. It can be difficult (or impossible!) for you to say no when someone needs something, even if you have nothing to give. Giving beyond your means will cause a sort of burnout, and can even lead to debt and other financial distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-give-less-than-your-means&quot;&gt;You give less than your means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you give less than your means, you are giving less than you could afford to, and more importantly you give less than your values would normally lead you to. It can cause anxiety and guilt, because you may know you aren’t spending your money according to your values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-people-give-out-of-balance-with-their-situation&quot;&gt;Why do people give out of balance with their situation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be many reasons why people give out of balance from their means. Both over- and under-giving can be because of self-esteem issues: You don’t feel you have anything of worth to give, or perhaps you don’t feel &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; are worth taking care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving out of balance can also be because they are unclear in their financial situation. Or perhaps you so overwhelmed by the needs of the world, you shut down, and don’t give to anyone.
Remember, giving to yourself is giving too! Taking care of yourself helps those around you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding why you give out of balance to your means can help you understand how to change your situation. Listen to your heart! How can you best &lt;strong&gt;give&lt;/strong&gt; of yourself, after you have done enough to &lt;strong&gt;take care&lt;/strong&gt; of yourself first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-one-week-exercise&quot;&gt;A One Week Exercise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-give-more-than-your-means&quot;&gt;If you give more than your means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a powerful exercises I learned from the Wild Money course. For one week, put yourself on a “giving fast”. Do not give money to anyone or anything. Every time you would normally give but don’t, write it down. Write down to whom, how much, and how it made you feel to not give that money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week, you may be surprised by how you feel. One client told me she felt valuable and powerful. She started recognizing things she gives for that actually aren’t very well aligned to her values, because she didn’t have as strong an emotional reaction to not giving in those situations. Other things were clearly more aligned because it was quite painful to not give to them. At the end of the week, she went back to giving for those things she felt strongly about, and stopped the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another client noticed that she had to not help a friend out that she normally would have immediately given money to. She instead supported her friend emotionally as she looked for another way. As she watched this friend, she noticed she seemed to feel empowered that she had earned the money herself, instead of relying on a friend. The real gift was to allow her friend to work and grow on her own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-give-less-than-your-means&quot;&gt;If you give less than your means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one week, commit to giving an amount of money every day. Give it to someone in need, like a homeless person, or to someone that it may delight. You can give a larger tip, or give to a charity. Whatever strikes your fancy that day. It could be $10, $20 or $50 a day. Whatever makes sense in your current financial situation. Every time you give that money away, write it down. Write who you gave it to, and how it made you feel to give the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find that giving regularly like this may bring up strong emotions, like it did for me. Whatever they are, write them down, and explore them further. They are probably trying to tell you something, maybe about your past, maybe about a misalignment between your behavior and your values. Whatever it is, try to follow it fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting into the habit of giving can open up a world of gratitude. You can start seeing the world in terms of how you can help. You have value that can help others! What a powerful feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;at-the-end-of-the-week&quot;&gt;At the end of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this exercise, look over what you wrote, and remember how you felt. Did you run into problems or strong emotions? Did you go back to your usual habits halfway through? Or did you feel content and happy? Whatever it was remember it and write it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing you can do is plan for her giving in your budget. Budgeting (especially &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;Envelope Budgeting&lt;/a&gt;) will allow you to find a balance that will allow for sustained giving over the rest of your life. It can help you understand whether your are giving within your means and in balance with your life, and can help you understand whether your are giving according to your values. It can also help you see how your increasing financial stability can help you be a more generous and giving person, without neglecting your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/29/How-To-Balance-Giving-With-Budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/29/How-To-Balance-Giving-With-Budgeting.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Envelope Budgeting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do people have trouble starting and using a budget? I think it starts with two words – Forecasting and Rigidity. Think about how you probably budget (if you budget). Maybe you take a piece of paper (or a spreadsheet, or Mint. It doesn’t matter the tool, just the method) and write something like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This months income: &lt;strong&gt;$3000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This months expenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Groceries: $300&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rent: $1000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilities: $40&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entertainment: $100&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: 2400&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first problem with budgeting like that is you are forecasting your income. In other words you wrote down money you don’t have, so you are starting the whole operation with a guess! Even if you have a reliable government job, you’re working with dollars that don’t yet belong to you. And that means that your budget is already starting off as a sort of theoretical document. What if instead you budgeted for all of your expenses using the money you already have? That shifts the conversation to something concrete. If I currently have $4000 in my bank accounts, then I can allocate that money to my expenses, and I know that right now, today, I could pay all of those bills and expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeting in the traditional way also is very rigid. At the end of the month how often did you actually hit those estimates for your expenses? I know I usually managed to blow at least one or two of them out of the water, which makes the whole rest of the budget suspect. If I overspent, where does that money come from? Do I take it from next month? I know that didn’t work, because I never would adjust my next months budget downward to compensate for it, if I even made it to a second month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before envelope budgeting, I would make a budget in a flurry of optimism, then by the middle of the month, I’d already have abandoned it. It was too theoretical and too rigid, and it made me feel bad that my life didn’t march to the perfect beat of my budget’s drum, rather then my budget flexing with my vibrant, dynamic life and changing priorities. And so I would just… give up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-does-envelope-budgeting-work&quot;&gt;How does envelope budgeting work?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Envelope budgeting asks you to gather all the money you have &lt;strong&gt;right now&lt;/strong&gt;. Then you take a pile of envelopes and label them with of all your bills, obligations, and nice-to-haves. Then you put money into each envelope, as much as you think you will need for that category until the next time you get more money. When you run out of money, you’re done budgeting. This method is also called “Zero-sum budgeting,” which means you budget every dollar you have, until you have zero money left to assign to an envelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you then go to the grocery store, you would just grab your groceries envelope and take it with you. Whatever money you have in the envelope is the maximum you can spend. You still have to think ahead (“How many grocery trips do I need to take before the next time I get more money?”), but it keeps you from accidentally spending, say, your utility money on groceries, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;living-in-the-now-and-flexibility&quot;&gt;Living in the now, and flexibility&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does this method solve the forecasting and rigidity problems? Well, we aren’t forecasting, because we are only using money we currently have to plan our budget. And the flexibility comes in from the simplicity of the system. Lets say your brother calls you, and says he would like to stop by for dinner tomorrow night. You want to cook him a nice dinner, so you make a list of ingredients you will need to buy at the store. You estimate you’ll need $25 more than you’ve budgeted for groceries. What should you do? Maybe you would normally put it on a credit card, and promise yourself you’ll sort it out later. But since you’re working with envelopes and only the money you have right now, you decide to take the $25 out of your entertainment envelope. There, now you don’t have to remember that you need to scrimp a bit, it will be obvious, because your entertainment envelope has less money in it! Easy peasy, no shame, and no slowly and sneakily putting yourself into debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;doesnt-it-sound-like-a-lot-of-work&quot;&gt;Doesn’t it sound like a lot of work!?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, yes it does. Envelope budgeting as a method was invented a while back, so using envelopes with cash was the easiest way to keep track. But now, most people use debit (or credit) cards for most of their transactions, so how can we implement the method in the modern world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found one program that implements envelope budgeting very well – &lt;a href=&quot;www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;You Need A Budget&lt;/a&gt; (YNAB). It is an amazing program that is online, and has a mobile app, so when you are at the grocery store, you can pop open the app to see how much you have allocated to your groceries category (analogous to the envelope). They have a 34 day trial, and I highly encourage you to try it out. Their online tutorials and classes are amazing, and their support is top-notch, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;projecting-and-planning&quot;&gt;Projecting and planning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing people ask me is, “Well, if we’re not supposed to forecast, how are we supposed to plan for the future?” When I use the word “forecasting,” I just mean planning our month using money we haven’t yet received. We can plan by using categories for our goals. Just like you will have a &lt;em&gt;Groceries&lt;/em&gt; category, you can have savings categories, like &lt;em&gt;New Car&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Emergency Fund&lt;/em&gt;. As you get money in, you can chose to add money to those categories. They will get bigger and bigger until you reach your goal, then you can spend it for its purpose, or, if like your &lt;em&gt;Emergency Fund&lt;/em&gt; its purpose is to sit there an act as a cushion, that’s fine, too. You don’t have to spend it, just like you don’t have to spend the money you have in an envelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve skipped over a few other issues I have with traditional budgeting. For example, we tend to be &lt;strong&gt;far&lt;/strong&gt; too optimistic about our expenses. But for now, this gets you started on a whole new way of thinking about your budget. Remember, you don’t need to feel bad if your life isn’t fitting your budget. Your budget is supposed to be flexible enough to change with your life, instead of making you feel bad for your priorities changing over time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Five Whys</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the hardest part of repairing your relationship with money is understanding what the issue is in the first place. Is it something to do with your family history? Do you have a misalignment between your expenses and your values? Do you have different goals and ideas then your partner does, leading to friction and even fighting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you trace your problems to an issue like the above, it can be really hard to dig into what’s really going on, and how to fix it. When I get stuck trying to figure out why I’m resistant to something I know would be good for me, I sit down with a blank sheet of paper and use the “Five Whys” technique. I write down the problem, then below write down “Why?”. When I write the answer, I write down “Why?” below that. Do that five times, and you may be getting close to the root cause. Here’s an example that I’m having trouble with right now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I keep “stealing” from my savings account to pay for silly things like coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Because I like going to get coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Because I work alone, and it’s nice to be around people sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Because I’m an introvert, so I find it easier to go to a public place where I don’t really have to interact with people.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh boy, it’s starting to get hard now. Why don’t I want to work harder on being out with people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Well… it’s so hard to connect with my old friends when they work a regular J.O.B. Also, I feel like I’m not able to work when I’m alone.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m afraid I’m not getting enough done with starting my new business. I feel guilty that I don’t have more to tell my friends about how I’m doing. I don’t want to confront failure, so it’s easier to be alone among people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahhhh, now I’m starting to get somewhere. And it’s not at all where I expected this to go! In the fourth why I gave two different answers, so I chose to go with the first one for now. It’s worth it to go back and do this again with the second answer, because I may uncover some more interesting tidbits. Bt right now, I wanted to explore my first answer. I’m basically spending money on coffee because I’m afraid of failure. This is something that is way more addressable then my original frustration. How do I confront this fear of failure, instead of drowning it in coffee? That’s a post for another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this simple technique helps you dig further into your personal issues with money. Remember, personal finance is mostly  about the personal, less about the finance. When you are emotionally equipped to deal with your finances, they tend to start falling into line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: you can find out more about the history of this technique on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_Whys&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/15/The-Five-Whys.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/15/The-Five-Whys.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Financial Freedom!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a money coach. I help people understand their personal finances, align their financial situation with their values, and help create financial peace for themselves and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the largest gaps in education at all ages and levels is personal finance. Money is important in all facets of our lives, and yet how many of us have had classes or education in how to manage our money? I’m willing to bet that very few of those of you reading this have had any kind of formal or informal education in personal money management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have been taught what you know by your parents, either by what they’ve told you, or just by observing their behavior from afar. Maybe you watched them argue about money, or make poor decisions. Maybe you saw them make great decisions, but you don’t know why or how you made them, so you can’t replicate their success yourself. Whatever it may be, I can help. I can teach you how to budget (there’s that big bad word!), but not to limit you, but instead budget from a place of freedom and flexibility. I believe that your budget should follow and support your life, not be a rigid instrument to beat you up when you don’t “follow” it properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will create a series of weekly articles, tips and tricks for how to get control of your finances, without having to be a math wiz, and without feeling guilty about your past or your decisions. Sign up in the box to the right to get these articles straight to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Cecilia Case, Money Coach&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/08/Welcome-To-Financial-Freedom.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/08/Welcome-To-Financial-Freedom.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>