<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bountiful Money</title>
    <description>Save money, budget according to your values, and experience financial bliss</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Debt a Universal Constant?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I’ll be in debt until I die.”
“Everyone is in debt.”
“I’ll always have a car loan. I can’t afford to buy a car with cash!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debt is a universal constant, never to be escaped and never to be changed, like Death and Taxes, right? Over the years, I’ve noticed that there seems to be a large group of people out there that accept debt as a constant in their lives that can never be eliminated. “Well, that’s just the way it is, right? I have to get a loan to get a car. And by the time I pay this one off, I’ll need a new car, with a new loan.” But is that really true? Is debt really inevitable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear people talk this way, it brings up a few things in my mind. Firstly, there is a sense of defeat in this sort of talk. It implies that you have already given up on a debt-free lifestyle. Not only that, there is an implication that you can’t even try, because it’s quite simply impossible. Sometimes it makes sense that they’ve come to this conclusion - it comes from looking around you and seeing everyone you know in debt. It’s a small step to think that if everyone you know is in debt, it must be impossible to be debt-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But thinking like this closes off your options. You’ve already decided that you’re going to fail, sometimes even before you’ve tried! Don’t get me wrong, I am not trying to minimize the pain of being in debt. Having five or six figures of debt is absolutely a tough row to hoe. Getting out of debt is truly one of the hardest things that most people do with regard to their money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once you get out of debt, it is absolutely possible to &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; debt-free. You can take me for an example. I started my adult life by going to college. During that time I started accumulating student loans. I don’t remember anymore what the original amount was exactly, but I think it was about $40,000 all told. I was lucky that as soon as I was out of college my husband and I both got a good paying jobs. But I also got a credit card, and while I didn’t use it much, I did put a little on in it, and sometimes the balance would inch up a bit. I didn’t make my student loans a priority, so they lingered for years, accumulating more interest then was really necessary if I had concentrated on paying them off. Instead, my husband and I got car loans, and we bought a house. We were always pretty sensible, keeping the loan amounts low, and taking advantage of our good credit to keep the interest rates pretty low. But we weren’t paying attention to our finances, so credit card debt would creep up, then we’d pay them off, just to right back to using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started getting serious about repairing my relationship with money, I could see that getting out of debt was the first step. But I also realized that I wanted to stay out of debt. I knew that our mortgage wasn’t too bad of a debt, and had a small interest rate, so I decided to pay off all our student loans, car loans, and credit card debt, and then I resolved to never use debt unless it was a conscious decision that made financial sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After paying off all of our loans in 2015, we only took out loans twice. Once to buy a boat, that is now completely paid for, and once to lease an electric car (yes, leases are loans!). They were both thoughtful decisions that worked to our advantage and were relatively low risk loans. Since my divorce, we sold the house, and I have been debt free ever since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do I do it? I make decisions that make debt the decision of last resort. I always want to remember there are often alternatives to using debt. For example check out this awesome diagram:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://longliveirony.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/03SL2012BuyerarchyofNeeds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Buyerarchy of Needs&quot; /&gt;
The idea is you work from bottom to top, so buying new is always your last option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question I always ask myself: “Can I wait to buy this until I have the money for it?” Sometimes, like with clothing or household goods the answer is an easy yes. Sometimes, like with a house, then answer is often an automatic no. But it is always good to ask the question and challenge yourself to find creative ways of getting what you need without going into debt. Buying a car is a good example. Most people automatically assume they will have to buy a car with a loan. But do you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need a loan? Would an older car that is in good shape do you just as well? And if you need a loan, can you put a &lt;strong&gt;giant&lt;/strong&gt; down payment on it, so that you can pay it off as quickly as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this article has helped you see that there are often alternatives to using debt, and that debt is not a given in this world. There are many people who live debt-free, and you can, too! One last thing I want to say; being debt-free is &lt;strong&gt;worth it&lt;/strong&gt;. I have never been so stress free in my life. It can be annoying to not always have the nicest, shiniest thing. But the freedom of knowing I don’t owe anyone else anything is so much better than a spangly new phone, or a giant SUV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/13/Is-Debt-A-Universal-Constant.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/13/Is-Debt-A-Universal-Constant.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SpiralStaircase.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SpiralStaircase.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SpiralStaircase.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SpiralStaircase.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Three Pillars to a Healthy Relationship with Money</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last post, I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html&quot;&gt;the three symptoms of money issues&lt;/a&gt;. If you think you have a problem with your money, the next question becomes, what can you do about it? So today I’d like to talk a little about the three pillars to concentrate on when healing your relationship with money. This will give you a good base to start understanding the steps you’ll need to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the time that I took to heal my own relationship with money, I developed a theory that there are three aspects to a relationship with money that must all be addressed in order to create a healthy and stable relationship with your money. If you don’t have all three pillars in place, you will find it difficult to truly change how you work with money. So what are those pillars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;heal-your-old-money-stories&quot;&gt;Heal your old money stories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, and possibly the most important pillar is understanding and healing your old money stories. What is a money story? It is that little voice in your head that was written a long time ago and tells you how to feel about money. Do you ever hear a little voice in your head that says one of these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Rich people are greedy”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Poor people are lazy”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m terrible with money”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m not good with numbers, that must be why I can’t hold onto money”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Spending money on myself is self-indulgent”
And of course, there are thousands more stories you could be telling yourself. Some might even be good stories:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m worthy of having a good job that pays me well.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I can balance saving money with enjoying my life now.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever stories you have in your head, they probably developed when you were a child. They came from your parents, teachers, and peers. Unfortunately, they may not have always been the stories those people &lt;strong&gt;meant&lt;/strong&gt; to be telling you. But when you are a kid, you were a sponge. You saw everything, and incorporated them into your worldview. And because you probably did’t have a solid financial education, you never had a chance to examine those stories and assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first pillar of healing your relationship with money is to take out those old stories and examine them. Where did you get these stories? And did are they still useful to you, or are they actually harming your ability to make and spend money in a satisfying and rewarding way? And if not, what would be a better story that would serve you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learn-techniques-to-manage-your-money-with-joy&quot;&gt;Learn techniques to manage your money with joy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healing your emotional relationship with money is very important, and is often neglected by financial experts. But along with healing your emotions around money, it is important to learn a set of tools and techniques that will help you manage money. Healing your emotions without action isn’t going to be that helpful to you in the long term. So learning peaceful and useful ways of holding up your Money Mirror (which is what I call budgeting), developing a debt repayment plan that makes sense for your life, and setting up good savings strategies are all very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;establish-your-new-money-groove&quot;&gt;Establish your new money groove&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, now that you have a good relationship with money, and you have the tools to maintain that relationship, it is very important to groove in new money habits. A good relationship with money needs to be maintained over time. There is no reason for it to be a fight against yourself to maintain your new relationship with money, though. These habits are going to feel more and more natural over time. As you keep practicing your healthy relationship with money, and utilizing techniques that help you achieve your life goals, you will find that the habits will start falling into place most of the time. But it is important to keep checking in with yourself: Are you happy with your money? Are you feeling stressed out, or peaceful and accomplished?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pulling-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Pulling it all together&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through these three pillars, you may start seeing that the three pillars are interconnected. Working on your emotions may open up techniques or tools that would have previously made no sense. Or learning a new tool may make it easier for you to develop better habits. So as you can see, working on your relationship with money isn’t a linear thing, and there is no quick fix. It, like many things, are made up of a series of baby steps that lead you to your goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/27/Three-Pillars-To-A-Healthy-Relationship-With-Money.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/27/Three-Pillars-To-A-Healthy-Relationship-With-Money.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">columns.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">columns.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/columns.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/columns.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Five Steps to Thrive with Variable Income</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone, I’m so excited that I have been accepted to write a blog post for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womenwithmoxie.com&quot;&gt;Women With Moxie&lt;/a&gt;! You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womenwithmoxie.com/five-steps-to-thrive-with-variable-income/&quot;&gt;read it there&lt;/a&gt; and I have reposted here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been working on my own relationship with money for a few years before I decided to become a Money Coach and start my own business. I had been through highs and lows, made mistakes, and had personal triumphs. I felt pretty good about my relationship with money and was out of debt, so I figured starting my own business wouldn’t change things that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wrong!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was budgeting with a stable salary, I had to deal with varying expenses, nasty surprises, and changing priorities all the time. But when I became a small business owner, everything became variable, both coming in and going out. I didn’t know how much money I was going to have to budget with, so how could I make decisions at all? What could I do to tame the wild bronco ride of variable income? Well, I needed to turn my variable income into a stable income. It sounds easy to say it, but of course, it was harder than it sounded. It took me a while, but I created a reliable system that I use today that helps me budget consistently and reliably. And today I’m going to share with you the five steps I took to master my variable income as a business owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Separate your business and personal accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All your income goes into the business account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the variability of your income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a buffer in your business account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pay yourself a stable income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;separate-your-business-and-personal-accounts&quot;&gt;Separate your business and personal accounts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have already heard this. While separating your personal and business accounts is often touted as a good idea for IRS purposes, there is another reason that is more relevant here - when you separate your personal money from your business money, you can get clarity. When all the business money is in one place you can see much more clearly how your business is really doing. And you can more easily budget your personal money if it is isolated from the fluctuations of the business. And that is the key here for those with variable income. You want to isolate the variability in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;all-your-income-goes-into-the-business-account&quot;&gt;All your income goes into the business account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have separated the two accounts, then you need to make sure that all of your income goes into your business account. Again, we’re striving to isolate that variable income, so it is easier to understand it and manage it. This step isn’t complicated, but it is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;determine-the-variability-of-your-income&quot;&gt;Determine the variability of your income&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have clarity between your personal and business money, you can use that clarity to really understand the variability of your income situation. For those of you with a little variability in your income, I suggest you look back at your income for the past 6 months. If you have extreme variability or seasonal variability, like realtors or owners of construction businesses, it is probably best to look at the last 12 months of income. List your income for the six months, and find these numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highest month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowest month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Average of all the months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a bit of an idea of how much your business income really varies. Now, just because these were your numbers for the last few months doesn’t mean that is what will happen in the next six months, but you’re not looking for a perfect number here. You’re just trying to get an idea of the ebb and flow of your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you are going to want to do the same with your business expenses. If you have fairly consistent business expenses, you’ll be able to just use one number and subtract it from the high, low and average income to get what you have available to send to your personal account. But if it is more variable, it may be a little harder to figure out. When in doubt, I recommend overestimating your guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;build-a-buffer-in-your-business-account&quot;&gt;Build a buffer in your business account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can use that information to build an Income Buffer. An Income Buffer is a small amount of money that allows you to even out the income you send to your personal account. That money will help you stay out of debt in the low months, and keep you from overspending in the flush months. So let’s say your lowest month was a net of $2000, your highest was $5000, and your average was $3500. You want to shoot for sending $3500 to your personal account every month, no matter how good or bad your revenue was this month. You will use that $3500 every month to pay all of your personal expenses. The difference between your lowest number and your average is $1500, so now you know that you need to build a buffer of at least $1500 to survive a low month of $2000 without reducing your personal spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pay-yourself-a-stable-income&quot;&gt;Pay yourself a stable income&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the good part! When you’ve built that Buffer, you can start using it to stabilize your income. Let’s say the next month, you make a net of $3000. You’ll pull $500 from your income buffer so that you can still pay yourself $3500. If the next month you make $4200, you can put all but $3500 of it back into your Income Buffer. Remember, all of these numbers are after your business expenses (and taxes!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have a stabilized income, starting to budget your personal expenses becomes so much easier. You’ll find that you can plan for the future much easier, and you won’t have those horrible months where you have to tighten your belt to almost nothing, or worse, start taking on debt. Instead, you will have a smooth, dependable income, every month!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/12/Five-Steps-To-Thrive-With-Variable-Income.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/12/Five-Steps-To-Thrive-With-Variable-Income.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">MoneyInAJar.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">MoneyInAJar.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/MoneyInAJar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/MoneyInAJar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Are The Top Three Symptoms Of Money Issues?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I get started with my article this week, I’d like to ask you to please forward these articles to anyone you think might benefit from them. I want to spread the word that a truly healthy relationship with money is possible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are working with a subject as important as money, it can sometimes be hard to even know if you have a problem. How can you tell if you are doing well, or if there really is something that you could do better? In this article I want introduce the top three symptoms that can help you identify if you need to improve your relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;feelings-of-guilt-or-shame-around-your-spending-decisions&quot;&gt;Feelings of guilt or shame around your spending decisions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you spend emotionally? Do you horde money because you’re afraid to make the wrong decision? Feeling guilt or shame around your money is your body and mind telling you that there is something wrong. I like to say that guilt and shame is often a symptom of a lack of alignment of your money decisions and your life values. The further your spending is away from your fundamental values, the stronger the feelings of guilt and shame will be. As I work with clients, we do a lot of work on releasing guilt and shame both by exploring their money stories as well as working to more deeply understand their values and realigning your spending with those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at this stage, it can be a useful indicator: If you feel guilt and shame around money, it probably means your relationship with money is currently unhealthy. The next step is become forgiving to yourself, while understanding what your current money situation is, so that you can make decisions that are more aligned with your values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-paycheck-to-paycheck-cycle&quot;&gt;The paycheck-to-paycheck cycle&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahhhhh, the paycheck-to-paycheck cycle. For those of you that have experienced it or it’s bruiser cousin the debt-spiral, I probably don’t need to say very much here. If you are just squeaking by every month, if you are relieved to see your paycheck come in every month, or you know that a delay of even a few days could sink your whole financial house of cards, then you already know how stressful and nerve-wracking being in this situation is. And the thing is, while it is sometimes a problem with too low income, it is just as often an issue with over-spending, or (here it is again!) lack of clarity about spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a paycheck-to-paycheck cycle, often the first step is getting clarity. I’m not trying to say it is easy. I know from personal experience that it is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much easier to say than do. But I can tell you, it is possible to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lack-of-clarity&quot;&gt;Lack of clarity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how much debt you have? Do you know the minimum you need to spend each month to survive? Do you know how much you are worth? If you have a business, are your business finances separated from your personal finances?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a lack of clarity surrounding your money is my number one symptom of an unhealthy relationship with money. It indicates that you might be pushing away your finances, and not looking deeply into whether you have a plan in place that is working for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-can-you-do-about-it&quot;&gt;What can you do about it?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to look at your finances clearly is also the first step to healing your relationship with money! You might be surprised how gaining clarity on your money will actually bring you relief from money stress. Even if the overall picture is not what you hoped, just knowing helps you understand what you can do to bring yourself forward to the financial goals you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is knowing you want to improve how you work with money! Now that you know, you can narrow it down a bit. Do you need to focus on debt? Do you want to stop compulsive spending? Do you want to let go of guilt and shame and have a healthy relationship with money? Once you know what the first step is, you can start working on healing your relationship with money, one day at a time. In an upcoming article, I’m going to talk about my philosophy for a healthy relationship with money. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">WalletSqueeze.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">WalletSqueeze.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WalletSqueeze.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WalletSqueeze.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fight the Overwhelm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I hear a lot of different emotions when I talk with my clients. Money is so connected to most parts of our lives that it is actually very difficult to separate it from how we conduct our lives, and the events that go on in our lives. We work to get money, which we then turn around and spend, both on things that are deeply important to us, and on things that are of almost no importance at all. And sometimes that wheel gets to be going faster and faster, until we feel like we might fly right off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That’s overwhelm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because our money lives are so complex, it can start feeling like we are juggling grumpy gerbils (Not that I would &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; do something like that!) and we’re just trying to stay ahead of the next disaster, or the next surprise in our lives. And what is one of the biggest contributors to this feeling of overwhelm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest contributor to feeling overwhelmed, it not knowing the outcomes to a situation will be bad or good, and not knowing what that might look like. So let’s take a look at a semi-fictionalized example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane graduated three years ago, and she has big student loans. She hates the feeling of debt, so she has mostly pushed it out of her mind, but sometimes, the fear comes cropping up. How will she every pay them off? What if she needs help, who can she ask? And most of all, she’s even lost track of how much she has in student loan debt, which spirals the feeling of overwhelm into the stratosphere. It can be hard, but sometimes even the act of finding out how “bad” the bad situation is can calm the emotions. When she finally worked up the nerve to call her loan company, she finds out it is $15,000. Well, that is bad of course, but it could be much worse and now that she knew, she could start putting a plan in place, one that put her in the drivers seat, and will get her out of debt over time. She also told them over the phone that she was getting control of her loans, and is there anything they would recommend she do to get into good standing with the company. They gave her several useful tips that helped calm her even further. Even though she hadn’t paid a single cent since the phone call, she already felt better, because she knew where she stood, and she was ready to create a usable plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have all felt overwhelm in our lives, especially around finances. The most important step to releasing that feeling is to start getting true clarity on your situation. Remember, managing your money is not about guilt and shame for the past. It is about starting from right now, and finding clarity and control. You can do this!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/16/Fight-The-Overwhelm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/16/Fight-The-Overwhelm.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Stacks.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Stacks.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Stacks.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Stacks.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My yearly review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned last year, I’m not big on New Year Resolutions. But making goals and reviewing them is very important and can really clarify your values and your money situation. The past few years, I’ve done an informal, high level yearly review of my financial situation, and it’s really helped me gain a perspective of how my goals change over time. I’d like to share with you my 2018 review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my list of financial goals for this last year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be making enough money with my own business to sustain myself at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html&quot;&gt;Bare Bones Number&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And if I haven’t achieved that, have a part-time in a related field to continue growing and expanding professionally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay debt-free!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contribute to my retirement funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a retirement portfolio worth $xyz. [Author note: I have removed the amounts for this goal, but I’ll talk about whether or not I have achieved it, and how it worked for me]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this list compare to where I stand right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-making-enough-money-with-my-own-business-to-sustain-myself&quot;&gt;Be making enough money with my own business to sustain myself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOT YET. This has been my number one job this year. But I look back and I don’t even recognize myself. I had no one to look to as a role model for being a small business owner. Neither of my parents owned a business, and I don’t have friends that own their own business, either. It has been a crazy steep learning curve, but I now consider myself a business owner and entrepreneur. I am not yet in the black. But I am proud of myself for two things; I have not gone into debt while starting my business, and I have learned so much this past year that I actually feel like a business owner! I know how to market and sell in a way that is in alignment with my values, and how to stand in my self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-if-i-havent-achieved-that-have-a-part-time-in-a-related-field-to-continue-growing-and-expanding-professionally&quot;&gt;And if I haven’t achieved that, have a part-time in a related field to continue growing and expanding professionally&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOPE, I didn’t do this. Even though I haven’t quite achieved point one yet, I am on track to do so. I want to make sure every ounce of my energy is going into that goal right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stay-debt-free&quot;&gt;Stay debt-free!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YES! I have done this so far! This is a huge achievement for a small business owner, let me tell you. There is no shame in getting a business loan, and if I end up needing one, I’ll certainly get one, but I really want to make a go of this without debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;contribute-to-my-retirement-funds&quot;&gt;Contribute to my retirement funds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOPE! I have set this aside until the first goal is achieved. I am ok with this because I am already ahead of the game with retirement investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-a-retirement-portfolio-worth-xyz&quot;&gt;Have a retirement portfolio worth $xyz&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOT QUITE. Because I haven’t been contributing, and the market hasn’t been stellar, I think it’s probably only a little over where I was last year. But seeing as I’m quite a bit ahead for my age, and I’m committed to changing the trajectory of my life, I’m totally OK with letting this one ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-else-happened-this-year&quot;&gt;What else happened this year?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My ex-husband and I still have a lovely relationship. This is so important to me, and we’ve both invested a lot of time and energy in being supportive of one another in our new quests and achievements. He’s been one of my biggest cheerleaders, and I’m so proud of his new job in the space industry! I know that is the fulfillment of a childhood dream for him.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I invested in a Business Coach. As a coach, one should always be investing in coaches (the general advice I’ve always heard is never hire a coach that doesn’t have a coach of their own!). She has revolutionized how I do business. I am streamlined, and probably ten times as effective as I was this time last year, all because of her.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have also taken this opportunity to practice being more present with my friends. I have a solid group of long term friends, and I want to make sure to nurture those relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-conclusions-can-i-draw-from-this-review&quot;&gt;What conclusions can I draw from this review?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at how many places I “failed”! I only have one goal that is an unqualified success. But did I really fail? Heck no, of course not! I have grown so much, changed my path and my perspective, and have become a more confident person. My goals were helpful, because setting them gave me a path, but if I had been too rigid, I wouldn’t have been flexible, and open to new opportunities. So I’m delighted with where I am, and I’m excited for the next year to start. As I said last year, it’s remarkable where I am this year as compared to last year. I feel like a completely different person. I’m confident in ways I never would have thought to ask for, and I’m more aware of how to heal some other parts of my life that I haven’t quite gotten to, yet. This year has most certainly not been all kittens and cinnamon. But it has been one of the most productive and revealing years of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-my-goals-for-2019&quot;&gt;What are my goals for 2019?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My financial goals haven’t changed much over this last year. I am going to continue with a variation of what I had last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My list for 2019:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue to make my new business my primary source of income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be in the black with my business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep my expenses low while starting my business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-about-you&quot;&gt;What about you?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does your 2018 review look like? And what goals have you set for 2019?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/02/Yearly-Review.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/02/Yearly-Review.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Goals.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Goals.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Goals.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Goals.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Start Your New Year Ready For Bounty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re getting close to the end of the year! Now is a great time to take a beat, and look back on what we did last year, and what we want to do next year. After the new year dawns, I’ll tell you a little bit about my personal retrospective and goals for 2019, but first, take a little time to look backwards and forwards with your money life, so you’re ready to take on 2019!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is a great time to take out a piece of paper, or open a new document on your computer, and answer a few questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What were your financial goals last year?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you meet those goals?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What unexpected paths did your life take?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking forward, what goals would you like to set down for 2019?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put the piece of paper in a safe place that you’ll be able to find next year. I even put an appointment item on my calendar for the first week of every year, to remind myself to pull out my old goals and review my year, then make those new goals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like doing this exercise, because I think it is wonderful to celebrate things we have done throughout the year, but also because I like to celebrate the twists and turns my life has taken. There’s nothing to be ashamed of for not accomplishing our goals, especially if it came about because we took some other wonderful turn in our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celebrate the wins, but also relish the complexity and beauty of a life well lived!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2018/12/19/Start-Your-New-Year-Ready.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2018/12/19/Start-Your-New-Year-Ready.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">BarleySunrise.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">BarleySunrise.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/BarleySunrise.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/BarleySunrise.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why the taboo against talking about money hurts you</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’m saying anything too controversial when I say that our society in America has a taboo against talking about money. We all run into situations where talking about how much we make, how much we spend, or how much debt we are in is just &lt;em&gt;not talked about&lt;/em&gt;. I’m no expert on sociology, but I think these taboos are instilled very early in our lives, and they are sometimes buried very deeply, so deeply that when we pause and ask ourselves “Why?” the answer is often “Because it’s rude” or “Because that is what is always done”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember once when I had gotten my first job out of college. I was at a party with some close friends. I excitedly said how much I was making for my starting salary ($43,000 in 2003! I will always remember that number.) and one of the older women grumpily said, “It must be nice.” I was crushed. I certainly wasn’t trying to make anyone else feel bad. But I had broken the code: you don’t talk about how much you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-are-the-problems-with-this-taboo-against-talking-about-money&quot;&gt;So what are the problems with this taboo against talking about money?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-feelings-of-guilt-and-shame&quot;&gt;It reinforces feelings of guilt and shame&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can’t talk about money, it becomes something we feel ashamed about. We assume that things we can’t talk about are bad in some way, so we can start assigning guilt to ourselves and our feelings about money. In my situation at the party, it was clear to me that I was supposed to be ashamed for making so much money out of the gate. And I absorbed that lesson well. I felt so bad for being proud of doing well, and getting that salary. This is a terrible lesson to learn. For one thing, talking about your salary with coworkers can help expose imbalances in how people are getting paid, and that is a good thing. Companies need to pay their workers fairly, and they aren’t going to do it if we aren’t talking to each other. And for another, money should not be something to feel guilty about! Money is just a tool - the flow of money from one person to another is an inherently neutral event. It is what we do with that flow that is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-lack-of-understanding&quot;&gt;It reinforces lack of understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can’t talk to each other about money, then we can’t learn from others. If someone else makes a mistake and learns a better way, if they can’t talk about it, then I can’t learn from their mistake. And if I can’t learn the vast options that are out there, I might assume that the way I saw my family work with money is the only way, even if they had a dysfunctional relationship with money. The more we talk to each other, the more we can all learn and get better together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-isolation&quot;&gt;It reinforces isolation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not talking about money doesn’t just isolate us from useful knowledge, it can also isolate us from others in different ways. If we can’t talk to each other about a subject, then how can we display empathy? When someone is in trouble, talking to others can be an important part of healing, but if they can’t do that then they will become isolated. And that is a scary place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-we-break-through-this-taboo&quot;&gt;How do we break through this taboo?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be hard to change an entire culture, but I do think that this one thing is changing over time. The best thing you can do is individually try to make a difference by starting to talk about money in your own life. Try talking about your salary with coworkers. Ask your friends for advice when you have a financial decision to make. And offer a kind, open listening ear when someone else is having trouble with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recommend making a money accountability buddy. Find someone that has a similar philosophy, and ask them if you could both talk about your money goals, and use each other for accountability. Get together for coffee once a month with them, and talk about what is working and what isn’t working in your money lives. Practicing with just one person you trust can help you both so much!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2018/12/05/Money-Taboo.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2018/12/05/Money-Taboo.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">TopSecret.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">TopSecret.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TopSecret.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TopSecret.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stop budgeting, start holding up your Money Mirror</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What feelings come up when I say the word “Budget”? If you are like most people, the words are often negative: restrictive, guilt, shame, hard, daunting, discouraging. I completely understand those emotions and feelings. I have had most of them myself with regard to this bad word: &lt;strong&gt;budget&lt;/strong&gt;. Why is it we are all told to budget, but then most of us have such negative feelings surrounding the process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because budgeting done in the normal way &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; restrictive! It is a process that can guilt us and shame us! We write down our income, we estimate our expenses, then we cross our fingers and hope it all goes well. When something inevitably changes or goes wrong, instead of the budget helping us flex with it, it stares back at us with big red negative numbers and seems to imply that it’s our fault that our life changed, or our priorities changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to suggest a mindset shift. Instead of budgeting, let’s talk about holding up our money mirror. When we hold up our money mirror, we are simply asking the question: “Does our spending align with our values?” It isn’t about guilt, or about “I should…” It is simply “Is this close to my values, or far away from them?” This simple shift can completely revolutionize how we think about money, and about the act budgeting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2018/11/21/Stop-Budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2018/11/21/Stop-Budgeting.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Budget.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Budget.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Budget.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Budget.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Join the new Money Empowerment Tribe!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am so honored! I held the first Money Empowerment Monthly meeting last week, and it was so fantastic! I had a chance to share the three keys to how to heal your relationship with money, and I had a blast! I got to present to an amazing group of folks in all of stages of life that are ready to transform their money relationship. I can’t believe how fantastic they all were, and I’m so excited for the next meeting. Going forward, the meeting is going to be a roundtable discussion. Bring your most pressing money issue or your most recent money success and I will facilitate an open discussion. We will talk about your money stories in a safe space, get support from others, and find new solutions to your money woes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Money-Empowerment-Monthly/&quot;&gt;Money Empowerment Monthly&lt;/a&gt; is designed to be an open and safe environment for people to get together and help each other change their relationship with money. If you are in Portland or know someone who is, I would like to invite you to the next meeting November 28th at 5:30pm at CENTRL Eastside. It is $15 if you sign up early, and $20 at the door!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2018/10/30/Join-The-New-Money-Empowerment-Tribe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2018/10/30/Join-The-New-Money-Empowerment-Tribe.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SunriseTea.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SunriseTea.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SunriseTea.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SunriseTea.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>