<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bountiful Money</title>
    <description>Save money, budget according to your values, and experience financial bliss</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>The Five Things That Make Debt Bad Or Good</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you heard the terms “bad debt” and “good debt”? Take a moment before you read on, and answer this question for yourself. What are the things that make debt “bad?” And what are the things that make debt “good?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always hated the terms bad debt and good debt for a couple of reasons. One is, everyone’s definition is different, so we all often end up talking at cross purposes, and creating more confusion than is necessary. The other is I think it lays moral implications on top of something where it isn’t useful. That especially becomes a problem if it intensifies your feelings of guilt and shame around your money situation. So when you were thinking about what makes debt bad, what characteristics did you think of? Here’s some things that came up in my mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High interest rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High risk (i.e. will I really be able to pay this off?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Used to buy things that I didn’t need, or that I should have saved for first (i.e. consumer debt)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsecured credit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I think of “good” debt I thought of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low interest rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low risk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mortgages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business loans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good debt to income ratio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leveraged debt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look at these lists, I notice a couple of things. One, most of these are hard to quantify. Exactly how low does an interest rate have to be, for it to be “good?” And others had ore to do with how they are used, not so much about the debt itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;is-this-really-a-useful-way-of-looking-at-debt&quot;&gt;Is this really a useful way of looking at debt?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d say that these criteria are so subjective that thinking of debt as good or bad really isn’t useful. And even more important, it implies that there are debts that you should feel guilty or ashamed to have. There are debts that are going to be harder to pay off, or may have been used for purposes that you now think weren’t worth the risk of the debt, but feeling overwhelming feelings of guilt will only make it harder to pay off. The most important work when paying off debt often isn’t creating a debt plan. Often it is working through the feelings that the debt situation creates in you, so that you can be truly ready to release your debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;are-there-better-ways-of-thinking-of-debt&quot;&gt;Are there better ways of thinking of debt?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Absolutely! Especially when thinking about taking on new debt, think about these things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the debt secured or unsecured?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the item being purchased worth the price and risk of the debt?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the item going to generate consumer debt (i.e. credit cards) or going to generate something like a mortgage?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a solid plan in place to pay off the debt? Realistically, how likely is it you will be able to stick to the plan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it high interest or low interest?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will this debt help you generate money? Be &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; with this one. People misuse the word “investment” all the time. A car is not an investment. A rental property or business may be an investment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter what other people think is “good” debt or “bad” debt. What matters is whether this debt is useful to you, and this list can help you understand whether the debt is really worth it &lt;em&gt;for you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/06/19/What-Is-Bad-Debt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/06/19/What-Is-Bad-Debt.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">GoodBad.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">GoodBad.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GoodBad.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/GoodBad.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Three Reasons People Don't Want to Budget</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Back when I was healing my own relationship with money, I encountered all sorts of resistance from others any time I mentioned budgeting. “Eh, I have enough money, I don’t need to track it.” Or on the other side: “I don’t have enough money to budget.” “Budgeting cramps my style,” or the reverse, “budgeting makes me feel bad about myself.” Now let me say, not everyone &lt;strong&gt;has&lt;/strong&gt; to budget. But I know that even for those that aren’t paycheck-to-paycheck, or deeply in debt, budgeting can still revolutionize personal finances for most people if done well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most budget methods &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; restrictive, but don’t have to be that way! You can create budgets that are flexible, friendly, and aligned with your values. And if your budget is like that, many of the old excuses melt away!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-dont-have-enough-or-have-too-much-money-to-budget&quot;&gt;I don’t have enough (or have too much) money to budget&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonsense! Here’s a little secret - good budgets don’t track your money, they track your &lt;strong&gt;goals&lt;/strong&gt;. Do you have goals? Great! Then you can use a budget to maintain, track and attain your goals, at least as they pertain to money! Do you want to get out of paycheck-to-paycheck? Great budgets help with that. Do you want to make sure your money is making the maximum impact in your life? Fantastic! No matter what that looks like, whether it be retirement investing, saving for the luxuries in life, or creating a charitable foundation, budgeting is the first step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;budgeting-makes-me-feel-bad-about-myself&quot;&gt;Budgeting makes me feel bad about myself&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this one can be a hard thing. When you hold up your Money Mirror (i.e. look at your budget) it will reflect your current reality. And often we aren’t where we want to be, yet. It can be painful to look at. First of all, know that it’s true for everyone, especially when you’re starting your money mindset journey. Second of all, taking a clear look is the first step to healing your relationship with money, and creating a new reality that you are proud of. If you can get into the habit of taking a clear look at your financial situation, you will find that lots of other things start falling into place. I promise you, the pain will fade over time, to be replaced with freedom and control!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-dont-need-a-budget-im-doing-just-fine&quot;&gt;I don’t need a budget, I’m doing just fine&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This certainly is true for a lot of people. But I argue that clarity can make your currently comfortable financial situation and turn it into a &lt;em&gt;spectacular&lt;/em&gt; one. Take a moment and really look deep inside yourself. Are you getting everything accomplished that you would love to? Are you saving for every goal that would make you happy, as quickly as you would like to? Are you providing for your family in every way possible? Are you contributing money to every worthy charity and cause that is important to you? If you said no to any of these things, then a budget might help you get closer to these loftier goals that you have for yourself. Who knows, you may find yourself one day starting a charitable foundation of your own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons of reasons why people don’t want to budget, but I think that the benefits far outweigh the emotional stress that it initially puts on you. What do you think, are you ready to give budgeting a try?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/05/22/Three-Reasons-People-Dont-Want-To-Budget.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/05/22/Three-Reasons-People-Dont-Want-To-Budget.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Budget.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Budget.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Budget.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Budget.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pick One Thing and Work On It</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked with clients for a while now, and one thing I see over and over again is &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2019/01/16/Fight-The-Overwhelm.html&quot;&gt;overwhelm&lt;/a&gt;. Our lives are so complicated, juggling family, work, leisure time (if we’re lucky!) a second job or business, kids, unreasonable customers… I don’t need to tell you this, you already know it. And the more we pile on, the more we sink into the details and the harder it is to see the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we start flailing around. Work on something for five minutes, then spring to the next thing. Shout at our kids while we try to write an email to the boss. We’re proud of “multitasking” yet we’re aware that we don’t really give anything our full focus, so we have this suspicion that we’re really not doing our best work at anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh my gosh, I’m stressing myself out just typing this! But I’m trying to make a point - if you are chaotic with your time, it is probable you are chaotic with your money, too. You may be tossing dollars at things hoping that you can improve all parts of your life, but there is no focus, so nothing gets better. In fact, things may be getting more chaotic and hard to deal with. And one day you turn around and realize you have ten credit cards carrying balances, and what do you really have to show for it? Are you traveling the way you always wanted to? Do you have the retirement funds you know you should have? What have those dollars really accomplished for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no simple solution for this, but I can tell you there is a simple first step: pick one thing and work on it. You can see an example of this idea in the Debt Avalanche (or its sister method “Debt Snowball”) method. If you don’t know what that is, allow me to give you a quick explanation. With Debt Avalanche, you list all of your debts. You write down the current balances, the interest rates, and the minimum payments for each. Then you arrange them in order of highest interest rate to lowest. Then, while you are paying for the minimums on all of the cards, you choose the debt at the top and throw all the extra money you have at it. When it is paid off, you take all of that money and go to the next debt on the list, and so on until they are all paid off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what you are doing is choosing one debt and creating a laser focus on it. All your efforts go towards paying off that one debt as fast as possible. And this has a couple of benefits. There is never any question of where extra money will go. You already know that, so you don’t have to expend any brainpower wondering or debating yourself. Also, it creates a clear reward path. As you pay off debts, you can see clearly how you are improving your situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can extend this technique to a lot of things. When you understand your &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html&quot;&gt;Bare Bones Number&lt;/a&gt;, you create this focus in your budget. You always know that you have to cover your rent, utilities, and groceries before anything else. That focus creates clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also use it for your savings. When you prioritize your savings goals, you can concentrate on the goals that will bring the most value to your life. And again, it creates clarity. You don’t need to wonder where that money is going, you’ve already made the decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want you to think that this is a magic bullet. It takes an understanding of your own values to create clear plans for yourself. And it takes discipline to carry out those plans over the long term. And that is where the rubber meets the road. But I do want to tell you it is possible to create clarity from chaos in your money life, and this is a great way to start!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/05/08/Pick-One-Thing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/05/08/Pick-One-Thing.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">ClearWater.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">ClearWater.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ClearWater.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/ClearWater.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Origins of the Word &quot;Mortgage&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I ran across a little piece of information recently that stopped me in my tracks. Did you know that the word &lt;em&gt;mortgage&lt;/em&gt; translates to &lt;em&gt;death contract (or pledge)&lt;/em&gt; in French? Wow! If you are anything like me, that provokes a strong emotional reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, debts are a powerful tool, like a sharp knife. It can be used as a tool, but it can also cause great damage and so they must be used cautiously and respect for the power they imply. And a mortgage is a good example of that power – the power to get you into a house now, while also creating a responsibility that will last for thirty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve read that a mortgage is so called because the deal dies either when the debt is paid, or when payment fails, which makes some sense, and is a bit less dramatic than the implication. But I don’t think it is an accident that such dramatic language is used to describe a debt. Does the term “death contract” change how you feel about your debts?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/04/24/The-Origins-Of-The-Word-Mortgage.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/04/24/The-Origins-Of-The-Word-Mortgage.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">House.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">House.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/House.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/House.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are You Afraid To Look At Your Debt?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my last post I wrote a bit about changing our perceptions about the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2019/03/13/Is-Debt-A-Universal-Constant.html&quot;&gt;inevitability of debt&lt;/a&gt;, but today I want to talk about a common problem people have with debt: Fear of looking at your debt. When you can’t look at your debt, it is impossible to &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; anything about your debt! So let’s dive in and see why this fear exists, and what you can do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-do-you-fear-debt&quot;&gt;Why do you fear debt?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first question to answer within yourself is &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; don’t you want to look at your debt situation? It can be a variety of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear that the amount is larger then you imagine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear of confronting past spending&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anxiety of having to make a plan, or make changes in the present&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shame about any number of things, including the idea that somehow you should have known better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, know three things: These emotions are powerful, they are understandable, and &lt;strong&gt;you are not alone&lt;/strong&gt;. But the first step to changing your life is taking a clear look at what you would like to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;take-a-clear-view&quot;&gt;Take a clear view&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have some ideas of the powerful emotions surrounding your debt, I want you to take a moment. Close your eyes and say: “I am trying to protect myself by not looking at my debt. I understand that this is an attempt of my brain to keep me safe, but it is no longer serving me to avoid this. I am strong and powerful, and ready to understand where I stand.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I suggest taking out a piece of paper or your journal and start writing. Take a deep breath: how do you feel right now? What emotions are coming up, and where are they centered physically in your body? What is the strongest emotion?  And finally, write down something like this: “I forgive myself for avoiding my debt. I am a good person, and I am worthy of a debt-free life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;break-it-down&quot;&gt;Break it down&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is gathering the details of your debt information. That is beyond the scope of this article, but understanding a snapshot of your debt right now is the next step in creating a debt repayment plan. But before you do that, I want you to congratulate yourself for taking the steps to open yourself to your current financial situation. For many people, confronting their debt is the hardest part of improving their relationship with money. I’m so proud of you for taking this step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;do-you-need-help&quot;&gt;Do you need help?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are struggling with this step or any other, I recommend you reach out to a Money Coach. We can help you with the strong emotions surrounding personal finance, and help you gain the tools you need to change how you relate to money. If you’d like to learn more, please reach out to me, I’m here to help!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/04/10/Are-You-Afraid-To-Look-At-Your-Debt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/04/10/Are-You-Afraid-To-Look-At-Your-Debt.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">EmptyPockets.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">EmptyPockets.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/EmptyPockets.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/EmptyPockets.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Bank Of Mom And The Bank Of Dad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I have been working with the great people at &lt;a href=&quot;http://debt-payoff-planner.com&quot;&gt;Debt Payoff Planner&lt;/a&gt;, we have been having fun looking through data. One thing they pointed out to me was some interesting statistics relating to family loans. Often these loans are from a parent, which isn’t surprising, but something that did surprise me is some of them have an interest rate. In other words, the parents are charging their kids for their loans, which I found really surprising. Let’s dig into the data a bit more, and find out who lends their kids more often, Mom or Dad? And who charges more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we tallied up the data for 10,000 loans we found that the percentage of loans that were from “Mom &amp;amp; Dad,” “Mom,” “Dad,” “Grandma,” or “Grandpa,” was about 2.4%. That number may skew a bit low because it would make sense for folks to not add family loans into their debt payoff calculator especially if they aren’t being charged interest. We also might have missed some that were labeled differently, so we don’t want to take this data as gospel. But let’s take a closer look at the data we do have. Who loaned the most often?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/MomandDadLoans1.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mom holds more than half of the loans, more than all the other family loans &lt;strong&gt;combined&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then looked a little closer, and we noticed something strange. Most of the loans are at 0%, but we did notice a scattering of loans with an interest rate - 11 loans in total! But when you look at them you’ll find that only one of the interest-bearing loans is from “Mom &amp;amp; Dad” (for &amp;lt;2%), one for Dad (for &amp;lt; 4%) and all the rest are from “Mom”! And not only that, Mom’s interest rates ranged all the way up to 20%! I have to say, I’m completely stunned by that news. I guess Mom really knows how to put the screws to their kids (I’m kidding! Just kidding!). We have no way of knowing why some of these parents are charging such a high interest rate, but it does put a bit of a spin on what I thought I knew about family loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;paying-off-family-loans&quot;&gt;Paying off family loans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all very interesting, but the most important question may be: when you have a loan from family, when should you pay it off?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great question, and the answer is often very personal. But there are two major things to consider: The math, and the relationship. If you look strictly at the math, the vast majority of family loans have no interest rate at all. If your loan is like that, it is tempting to shuffle it to the bottom of the list, below credit cards, car loans, and even mortgages and student loans. And if it was purely a mathematical decision, that would make sense. The loan isn’t costing you any more money, so it makes sense to concentrate on all of the other loans you have that &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; costing you money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it isn’t just a mathematical decision, it is a personal relationship decision, too. While many family lenders are perfectly happy to wait for a long time to see their money back, lent money can create a strain on relationships. As you are considering how to build your debt repayment plan, seriously consider the damage it may be doing to your relationship. If you feel that it is going to cause lasting harm, you might decide to put it higher on the list. But also consider what would make the situation better for both parties. Perhaps paying a minimal amount, but doing so regularly would show how serious you are about paying the money, and may lessen the tension without requiring you to put your credit card repayment plan on hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you may decide to hold a meeting with your parents, and have an open and frank discussion about your situation. Communicating your situation and plans with them, and then bringing them into the decision-making process may also be a really helpful step. But always consider, if this money is really standing between you and a good relationship with your parents, perhaps it is time to get serious about prioritizing your loan with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no right or wrong way of paying back family, but taking a look at the practical method, then examining how it will affect everyone involved and making sure there is good communication will make sure you find the best solution for you and your family.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/27/The-Bank-Of-Mom-And-The-Bank-Of-Dad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/27/The-Bank-Of-Mom-And-The-Bank-Of-Dad.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Parent.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">Parent.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Parent.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Parent.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Debt a Universal Constant?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“I’ll be in debt until I die.”
“Everyone is in debt.”
“I’ll always have a car loan. I can’t afford to buy a car with cash!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debt is a universal constant, never to be escaped and never to be changed, like Death and Taxes, right? Over the years, I’ve noticed that there seems to be a large group of people out there that accept debt as a constant in their lives that can never be eliminated. “Well, that’s just the way it is, right? I have to get a loan to get a car. And by the time I pay this one off, I’ll need a new car, with a new loan.” But is that really true? Is debt really inevitable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear people talk this way, it brings up a few things in my mind. Firstly, there is a sense of defeat in this sort of talk. It implies that you have already given up on a debt-free lifestyle. Not only that, there is an implication that you can’t even try, because it’s quite simply impossible. Sometimes it makes sense that they’ve come to this conclusion - it comes from looking around you and seeing everyone you know in debt. It’s a small step to think that if everyone you know is in debt, it must be impossible to be debt-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But thinking like this closes off your options. You’ve already decided that you’re going to fail, sometimes even before you’ve tried! Don’t get me wrong, I am not trying to minimize the pain of being in debt. Having five or six figures of debt is absolutely a tough row to hoe. Getting out of debt is truly one of the hardest things that most people do with regard to their money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once you get out of debt, it is absolutely possible to &lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; debt-free. You can take me for an example. I started my adult life by going to college. During that time I started accumulating student loans. I don’t remember anymore what the original amount was exactly, but I think it was about $40,000 all told. I was lucky that as soon as I was out of college my husband and I both got a good paying jobs. But I also got a credit card, and while I didn’t use it much, I did put a little on in it, and sometimes the balance would inch up a bit. I didn’t make my student loans a priority, so they lingered for years, accumulating more interest then was really necessary if I had concentrated on paying them off. Instead, my husband and I got car loans, and we bought a house. We were always pretty sensible, keeping the loan amounts low, and taking advantage of our good credit to keep the interest rates pretty low. But we weren’t paying attention to our finances, so credit card debt would creep up, then we’d pay them off, just to right back to using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started getting serious about repairing my relationship with money, I could see that getting out of debt was the first step. But I also realized that I wanted to stay out of debt. I knew that our mortgage wasn’t too bad of a debt, and had a small interest rate, so I decided to pay off all our student loans, car loans, and credit card debt, and then I resolved to never use debt unless it was a conscious decision that made financial sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After paying off all of our loans in 2015, we only took out loans twice. Once to buy a boat, that is now completely paid for, and once to lease an electric car (yes, leases are loans!). They were both thoughtful decisions that worked to our advantage and were relatively low risk loans. Since my divorce, we sold the house, and I have been debt free ever since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do I do it? I make decisions that make debt the decision of last resort. I always want to remember there are often alternatives to using debt. For example check out this awesome diagram:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://longliveirony.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/03SL2012BuyerarchyofNeeds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Buyerarchy of Needs&quot; /&gt;
The idea is you work from bottom to top, so buying new is always your last option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question I always ask myself: “Can I wait to buy this until I have the money for it?” Sometimes, like with clothing or household goods the answer is an easy yes. Sometimes, like with a house, then answer is often an automatic no. But it is always good to ask the question and challenge yourself to find creative ways of getting what you need without going into debt. Buying a car is a good example. Most people automatically assume they will have to buy a car with a loan. But do you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need a loan? Would an older car that is in good shape do you just as well? And if you need a loan, can you put a &lt;strong&gt;giant&lt;/strong&gt; down payment on it, so that you can pay it off as quickly as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this article has helped you see that there are often alternatives to using debt, and that debt is not a given in this world. There are many people who live debt-free, and you can, too! One last thing I want to say; being debt-free is &lt;strong&gt;worth it&lt;/strong&gt;. I have never been so stress free in my life. It can be annoying to not always have the nicest, shiniest thing. But the freedom of knowing I don’t owe anyone else anything is so much better than a spangly new phone, or a giant SUV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/13/Is-Debt-A-Universal-Constant.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/03/13/Is-Debt-A-Universal-Constant.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SpiralStaircase.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">SpiralStaircase.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SpiralStaircase.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SpiralStaircase.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Three Pillars to a Healthy Relationship with Money</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last post, I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html&quot;&gt;the three symptoms of money issues&lt;/a&gt;. If you think you have a problem with your money, the next question becomes, what can you do about it? So today I’d like to talk a little about the three pillars to concentrate on when healing your relationship with money. This will give you a good base to start understanding the steps you’ll need to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the time that I took to heal my own relationship with money, I developed a theory that there are three aspects to a relationship with money that must all be addressed in order to create a healthy and stable relationship with your money. If you don’t have all three pillars in place, you will find it difficult to truly change how you work with money. So what are those pillars?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;heal-your-old-money-stories&quot;&gt;Heal your old money stories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, and possibly the most important pillar is understanding and healing your old money stories. What is a money story? It is that little voice in your head that was written a long time ago and tells you how to feel about money. Do you ever hear a little voice in your head that says one of these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Rich people are greedy”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Poor people are lazy”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m terrible with money”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m not good with numbers, that must be why I can’t hold onto money”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Spending money on myself is self-indulgent”
And of course, there are thousands more stories you could be telling yourself. Some might even be good stories:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I’m worthy of having a good job that pays me well.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I can balance saving money with enjoying my life now.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever stories you have in your head, they probably developed when you were a child. They came from your parents, teachers, and peers. Unfortunately, they may not have always been the stories those people &lt;strong&gt;meant&lt;/strong&gt; to be telling you. But when you are a kid, you were a sponge. You saw everything, and incorporated them into your worldview. And because you probably did’t have a solid financial education, you never had a chance to examine those stories and assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first pillar of healing your relationship with money is to take out those old stories and examine them. Where did you get these stories? And did are they still useful to you, or are they actually harming your ability to make and spend money in a satisfying and rewarding way? And if not, what would be a better story that would serve you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learn-techniques-to-manage-your-money-with-joy&quot;&gt;Learn techniques to manage your money with joy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healing your emotional relationship with money is very important, and is often neglected by financial experts. But along with healing your emotions around money, it is important to learn a set of tools and techniques that will help you manage money. Healing your emotions without action isn’t going to be that helpful to you in the long term. So learning peaceful and useful ways of holding up your Money Mirror (which is what I call budgeting), developing a debt repayment plan that makes sense for your life, and setting up good savings strategies are all very important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;establish-your-new-money-groove&quot;&gt;Establish your new money groove&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, now that you have a good relationship with money, and you have the tools to maintain that relationship, it is very important to groove in new money habits. A good relationship with money needs to be maintained over time. There is no reason for it to be a fight against yourself to maintain your new relationship with money, though. These habits are going to feel more and more natural over time. As you keep practicing your healthy relationship with money, and utilizing techniques that help you achieve your life goals, you will find that the habits will start falling into place most of the time. But it is important to keep checking in with yourself: Are you happy with your money? Are you feeling stressed out, or peaceful and accomplished?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pulling-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Pulling it all together&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through these three pillars, you may start seeing that the three pillars are interconnected. Working on your emotions may open up techniques or tools that would have previously made no sense. Or learning a new tool may make it easier for you to develop better habits. So as you can see, working on your relationship with money isn’t a linear thing, and there is no quick fix. It, like many things, are made up of a series of baby steps that lead you to your goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/27/Three-Pillars-To-A-Healthy-Relationship-With-Money.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/27/Three-Pillars-To-A-Healthy-Relationship-With-Money.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">columns.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">columns.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/columns.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/columns.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Five Steps to Thrive with Variable Income</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone, I’m so excited that I have been accepted to write a blog post for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womenwithmoxie.com&quot;&gt;Women With Moxie&lt;/a&gt;! You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.womenwithmoxie.com/five-steps-to-thrive-with-variable-income/&quot;&gt;read it there&lt;/a&gt; and I have reposted here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been working on my own relationship with money for a few years before I decided to become a Money Coach and start my own business. I had been through highs and lows, made mistakes, and had personal triumphs. I felt pretty good about my relationship with money and was out of debt, so I figured starting my own business wouldn’t change things that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wrong!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was budgeting with a stable salary, I had to deal with varying expenses, nasty surprises, and changing priorities all the time. But when I became a small business owner, everything became variable, both coming in and going out. I didn’t know how much money I was going to have to budget with, so how could I make decisions at all? What could I do to tame the wild bronco ride of variable income? Well, I needed to turn my variable income into a stable income. It sounds easy to say it, but of course, it was harder than it sounded. It took me a while, but I created a reliable system that I use today that helps me budget consistently and reliably. And today I’m going to share with you the five steps I took to master my variable income as a business owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Separate your business and personal accounts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All your income goes into the business account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the variability of your income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a buffer in your business account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pay yourself a stable income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;separate-your-business-and-personal-accounts&quot;&gt;Separate your business and personal accounts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have already heard this. While separating your personal and business accounts is often touted as a good idea for IRS purposes, there is another reason that is more relevant here - when you separate your personal money from your business money, you can get clarity. When all the business money is in one place you can see much more clearly how your business is really doing. And you can more easily budget your personal money if it is isolated from the fluctuations of the business. And that is the key here for those with variable income. You want to isolate the variability in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;all-your-income-goes-into-the-business-account&quot;&gt;All your income goes into the business account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have separated the two accounts, then you need to make sure that all of your income goes into your business account. Again, we’re striving to isolate that variable income, so it is easier to understand it and manage it. This step isn’t complicated, but it is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;determine-the-variability-of-your-income&quot;&gt;Determine the variability of your income&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have clarity between your personal and business money, you can use that clarity to really understand the variability of your income situation. For those of you with a little variability in your income, I suggest you look back at your income for the past 6 months. If you have extreme variability or seasonal variability, like realtors or owners of construction businesses, it is probably best to look at the last 12 months of income. List your income for the six months, and find these numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highest month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lowest month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Average of all the months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a bit of an idea of how much your business income really varies. Now, just because these were your numbers for the last few months doesn’t mean that is what will happen in the next six months, but you’re not looking for a perfect number here. You’re just trying to get an idea of the ebb and flow of your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you are going to want to do the same with your business expenses. If you have fairly consistent business expenses, you’ll be able to just use one number and subtract it from the high, low and average income to get what you have available to send to your personal account. But if it is more variable, it may be a little harder to figure out. When in doubt, I recommend overestimating your guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;build-a-buffer-in-your-business-account&quot;&gt;Build a buffer in your business account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can use that information to build an Income Buffer. An Income Buffer is a small amount of money that allows you to even out the income you send to your personal account. That money will help you stay out of debt in the low months, and keep you from overspending in the flush months. So let’s say your lowest month was a net of $2000, your highest was $5000, and your average was $3500. You want to shoot for sending $3500 to your personal account every month, no matter how good or bad your revenue was this month. You will use that $3500 every month to pay all of your personal expenses. The difference between your lowest number and your average is $1500, so now you know that you need to build a buffer of at least $1500 to survive a low month of $2000 without reducing your personal spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pay-yourself-a-stable-income&quot;&gt;Pay yourself a stable income&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the good part! When you’ve built that Buffer, you can start using it to stabilize your income. Let’s say the next month, you make a net of $3000. You’ll pull $500 from your income buffer so that you can still pay yourself $3500. If the next month you make $4200, you can put all but $3500 of it back into your Income Buffer. Remember, all of these numbers are after your business expenses (and taxes!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have a stabilized income, starting to budget your personal expenses becomes so much easier. You’ll find that you can plan for the future much easier, and you won’t have those horrible months where you have to tighten your belt to almost nothing, or worse, start taking on debt. Instead, you will have a smooth, dependable income, every month!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/12/Five-Steps-To-Thrive-With-Variable-Income.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/02/12/Five-Steps-To-Thrive-With-Variable-Income.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">MoneyInAJar.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">MoneyInAJar.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/MoneyInAJar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/MoneyInAJar.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Are The Top Three Symptoms Of Money Issues?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I get started with my article this week, I’d like to ask you to please forward these articles to anyone you think might benefit from them. I want to spread the word that a truly healthy relationship with money is possible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are working with a subject as important as money, it can sometimes be hard to even know if you have a problem. How can you tell if you are doing well, or if there really is something that you could do better? In this article I want introduce the top three symptoms that can help you identify if you need to improve your relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;feelings-of-guilt-or-shame-around-your-spending-decisions&quot;&gt;Feelings of guilt or shame around your spending decisions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you spend emotionally? Do you horde money because you’re afraid to make the wrong decision? Feeling guilt or shame around your money is your body and mind telling you that there is something wrong. I like to say that guilt and shame is often a symptom of a lack of alignment of your money decisions and your life values. The further your spending is away from your fundamental values, the stronger the feelings of guilt and shame will be. As I work with clients, we do a lot of work on releasing guilt and shame both by exploring their money stories as well as working to more deeply understand their values and realigning your spending with those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at this stage, it can be a useful indicator: If you feel guilt and shame around money, it probably means your relationship with money is currently unhealthy. The next step is become forgiving to yourself, while understanding what your current money situation is, so that you can make decisions that are more aligned with your values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-paycheck-to-paycheck-cycle&quot;&gt;The paycheck-to-paycheck cycle&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahhhhh, the paycheck-to-paycheck cycle. For those of you that have experienced it or it’s bruiser cousin the debt-spiral, I probably don’t need to say very much here. If you are just squeaking by every month, if you are relieved to see your paycheck come in every month, or you know that a delay of even a few days could sink your whole financial house of cards, then you already know how stressful and nerve-wracking being in this situation is. And the thing is, while it is sometimes a problem with too low income, it is just as often an issue with over-spending, or (here it is again!) lack of clarity about spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a paycheck-to-paycheck cycle, often the first step is getting clarity. I’m not trying to say it is easy. I know from personal experience that it is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much easier to say than do. But I can tell you, it is possible to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lack-of-clarity&quot;&gt;Lack of clarity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how much debt you have? Do you know the minimum you need to spend each month to survive? Do you know how much you are worth? If you have a business, are your business finances separated from your personal finances?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a lack of clarity surrounding your money is my number one symptom of an unhealthy relationship with money. It indicates that you might be pushing away your finances, and not looking deeply into whether you have a plan in place that is working for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-can-you-do-about-it&quot;&gt;What can you do about it?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to look at your finances clearly is also the first step to healing your relationship with money! You might be surprised how gaining clarity on your money will actually bring you relief from money stress. Even if the overall picture is not what you hoped, just knowing helps you understand what you can do to bring yourself forward to the financial goals you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is knowing you want to improve how you work with money! Now that you know, you can narrow it down a bit. Do you need to focus on debt? Do you want to stop compulsive spending? Do you want to let go of guilt and shame and have a healthy relationship with money? Once you know what the first step is, you can start working on healing your relationship with money, one day at a time. In an upcoming article, I’m going to talk about my philosophy for a healthy relationship with money. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/2019/01/30/Three-Symptoms-Of-Money-Issues.html</guid>
        <media:title xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">WalletSqueeze.jpg</media:title>
        <media:description xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">WalletSqueeze.jpg</media:description>
        <media:content url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WalletSqueeze.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" type="image/jpeg" width="600"/>
       <media:thumbnail url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WalletSqueeze.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>