<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bountiful Money, LLC</title>
    <description>Save money, budget according to your values, and experience financial bliss</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Why the taboo against talking about money hurts you</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’m saying anything too controversial when I say that our society in America has a taboo against talking about money. We all run into situations where talking about how much we make, how much we spend, or how much debt we are in is just &lt;em&gt;not talked about&lt;/em&gt;. I’m no expert on sociology, but I think these taboos are instilled very early in our lives, and they are sometimes buried very deeply, so deeply that when we pause and ask ourselves “Why?” the answer is often “Because it’s rude” or “Because that is what is always done”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember once when I had gotten my first job out of college. I was at a party with some close friends. I excitedly said how much I was making for my starting salary ($43,000 in 2003! I will always remember that number.) and one of the older women grumpily said, “It must be nice.” I was crushed. I certainly wasn’t trying to make anyone else feel bad. But I had broken the code: you don’t talk about how much you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-are-the-problems-with-this-taboo-against-talking-about-money&quot;&gt;So what are the problems with this taboo against talking about money?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-feelings-of-guilt-and-shame&quot;&gt;It reinforces feelings of guilt and shame&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can’t talk about money, it becomes something we feel ashamed about. We assume that things we can’t talk about are bad in some way, so we can start assigning guilt to ourselves and our feelings about money. In my situation at the party, it was clear to me that I was supposed to be ashamed for making so much money out of the gate. And I absorbed that lesson well. I felt so bad for being proud of doing well, and getting that salary. This is a terrible lesson to learn. For one thing, talking about your salary with coworkers can help expose imbalances in how people are getting paid, and that is a good thing. Companies need to pay their workers fairly, and they aren’t going to do it if we aren’t talking to each other. And for another, money should not be something to feel guilty about! Money is just a tool - the flow of money from one person to another is an inherently neutral event. It is what we do with that flow that is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-lack-of-understanding&quot;&gt;It reinforces lack of understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can’t talk to each other about money, then we can’t learn from others. If someone else makes a mistake and learns a better way, if they can’t talk about it, then I can’t learn from their mistake. And if I can’t learn the vast options that are out there, I might assume that the way I saw my family work with money is the only way, even if they had a dysfunctional relationship with money. The more we talk to each other, the more we can all learn and get better together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-reinforces-isolation&quot;&gt;It reinforces isolation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not talking about money doesn’t just isolate us from useful knowledge, it can also isolate us from others in different ways. If we can’t talk to each other about a subject, then how can we display empathy? When someone is in trouble, talking to others can be an important part of healing, but if they can’t do that then they will become isolated. And that is a scary place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-we-break-through-this-taboo&quot;&gt;How do we break through this taboo?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be hard to change an entire culture, but I do think that this one thing is changing over time. The best thing you can do is individually try to make a difference by starting to talk about money in your own life. Try talking about your salary with coworkers. Ask your friends for advice when you have a financial decision to make. And offer a kind, open listening ear when someone else is having trouble with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recommend making a money accountability buddy. Find someone that has a similar philosophy, and ask them if you could both talk about your money goals, and use each other for accountability. Get together for coffee once a month with them, and talk about what is working and what isn’t working in your money lives. Practicing with just one person you trust can help you both so much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, make an &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendly.com/ceciliacase/initialconsult&quot;&gt;appointment&lt;/a&gt; for your &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; Money Empowerment Session! In one hour, you will have an opportunity to explore your relationship with money and a safe and supportive environment, and come out of it with a list of recommendations to take the next step towards a healthy relationship with money!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/12/05/Money-Taboo.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/12/05/Money-Taboo.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stop budgeting, start holding up your Money Mirror</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What feelings come up when I say the word “Budget”? If you are like most people, the words are often negative: restrictive, guilt, shame, hard, daunting, discouraging. I completely understand those emotions and feelings. I have had most of them myself with regard to this bad word: &lt;strong&gt;budget&lt;/strong&gt;. Why is it we are all told to budget, but then most of us have such negative feelings surrounding the process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is because budgeting done in the normal way &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; restrictive! It is a process that can guilt us and shame us! We write down our income, we estimate our expenses, then we cross our fingers and hope it all goes well. When something inevitably changes or goes wrong, instead of the budget helping us flex with it, it stares back at us with big red negative numbers and seems to imply that it’s our fault that our life changed, or our priorities changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to suggest a mindset shift. Instead of budgeting, let’s talk about holding up our money mirror. When we hold up our money mirror, we are simply asking the question: “Does our spending align with our values?” It isn’t about guilt, or about “I should…” It is simply “Is this close to my values, or far away from them?” This simple shift can completely revolutionize how we think about money, and about the act budgeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like more information, you can set up a free &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendly.com/ceciliacase/initialconsult&quot;&gt;Money Empowerment Session&lt;/a&gt; with me to learn more about how to apply budgeting to your life in a more peaceful way. And please come to the Money Empowerment Monthly meeting here in Portland! It is a safe environment where you can talk about your greatest money fears and issues in the safety of a facilitated peer group. You can sign up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Money-Empowerment-Monthly/&quot;&gt;Meetup&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/money-empowerment-monthly-tickets-52066447145&quot;&gt;Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;. The next meetup is November 28th at 5:30pm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/11/21/stop-budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/11/21/stop-budgeting.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Join the new Money Empowerment Tribe!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am so honored! I held the first Money Empowerment Monthly meeting last week, and it was so fantastic! I had a chance to share the three keys to how to heal your relationship with money, and I had a blast! I got to present to an amazing group of folks in all of stages of life that are ready to transform their money relationship. I can’t believe how fantastic they all were, and I’m so excited for the next meeting. Going forward, the meeting is going to be a roundtable discussion. Bring your most pressing money issue or your most recent money success and I will facilitate an open discussion. We will talk about your money stories in a safe space, get support from others, and find new solutions to your money woes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Money-Empowerment-Monthly/&quot;&gt;Money Empowerment Monthly&lt;/a&gt; is designed to be an open and safe environment for people to get together and help each other change their relationship with money. If you are in Portland or know someone who is, I would like to invite you to the next meeting November 28th at 5:30pm at CENTRL Eastside. It is $15 if you sign up early, and $20 at the door!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/10/30/Join-The-New-Money-Empowerment-Tribe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/10/30/Join-The-New-Money-Empowerment-Tribe.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Draw Strength From Your Tribe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you have nieces? I do, and they are amazing. Every time I see them, they remind me of the fearless person I was when I was a child, the person I always aspire to be now. My lovely sister has invited me to their soccer games, and every weekend I sit there on the sidelines watching, learning more about them, every single wet morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they first started this season, they did well, but they weren’t communicating, and it seemed to my untrained eyes like they were eleven girls out on the field, all doing their own thing. They were all good, but… they were’t a team. But this last match I watched was amazing. They were no longer eleven girls. They were one team. One &lt;strong&gt;tribe&lt;/strong&gt;. I watched them as they shouted instructions and advice to each other. They formed into strategic groups, then broke up and formed into different groups, as the situation warranted. They encouraged each other with every movement down the field, and every try for the goal. It’s only been 5 games, a little over a month, and they know each other so well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what have I learned from these hard-working pre-teens? I’ve learned that the power of women in sync, who are committed to teamwork without boundaries is the most powerful force in this world. It has made me appreciate anew the wonderful support group I have in my personal life. And it has made me appreciate the business network I’m building in my professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I want to take it one step further. I want to create a community of people that can support each other in their journey to a healthier relationship with money. So I’ve created a new Meetup group called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/Money-Empowerment-Monthly/&quot;&gt;Money Empowerment Monthly&lt;/a&gt; designed to be an open and safe environment for people to get together and help each other change their relationship with money. If you are in Portland or know someone who is, I would like to invite you to the inaugural meeting this October 24th (one week from now!) at 5:30pm at CENTRL Eastside. It is $15 if you sign up early, and $20 at the door!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/10/16/Strength-From-Your-Tribe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/10/16/Strength-From-Your-Tribe.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a Normal Month?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What is a Normal Month? Take a moment to think about what that means to you. Does it mean that you are spending exactly what you expect on your bills? Does it mean that you have no surprise expenses? Does it mean that you are able to pay your groceries in full, and have a little left over?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is, when was the last time you had a Normal Month? Many of you probably already know that it is a bit of a trick question. There is no such thing as a “Normal Month”. We live lives that are beautiful, complex, vexing, and wonderful. To have perfectly normal, average months, month after month, it would mean that we are living exactly normal, average, completely predictable lives. And even if that was possible, is that really what you want from your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure some unexpected events we could do without. The furnace breaks, or the alternator dies. We end up having less income than usual. Of course we don’t want that! But some things are &lt;strong&gt;wonderful&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, I got the chance to go on a spa day with friends recently. I chose to spend more, so that I could join them. Maybe family comes into town and you want to treat them, take them out to the local sights or to a nice restaurant for dinner. Maybe you get accepted to an artist retreat in France. Whatever it is, you don’t want to constrict your budget so much that you can’t take advantage of the exciting opportunities life tosses you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So don’t put it off: “I’ll start budgeting when I finally have a Normal Month.” Instead commit: “I’ll start budgeting now, so I never have to be caught flat-footed by the wild, crazy wonderful swings in life!”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/05/24/Normal-Month.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/05/24/Normal-Month.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Receiving Money Into Your Life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There once was a girl who got her first job out of high school. She had applied for a job as a sales clerk at the local department store, and she was so proud of herself when she was hired. She had put in the work to have a good resume, and did very well on the interview. She was nervous about her new job, but she knew she could do a good job. But… &lt;!--more--&gt; when she came home, her parents were angry. “Why do you need a job? You’re going to get a husband, and he’s going to take care of you. All you should be concerned about is finding that man.” She was crushed. She called the store and declined the job. Because of this incident, and many others like it, she decided she must not be worthy of receiving money. This feeling has plagued her her entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have money stories in our lives and in our past. Sometimes we have stories that encourage excessive spending habits. Sometimes they encourage miserly behavior. And sometimes, like the girl in our story, they tell us that we shouldn’t receive money into our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think back on your childhood and early adulthood. Do you have any stories that have made you feel like you aren’t worthy of receiving money into your life? What are the elements of the story that made you feel this way. Did someone put down your labors or work you did? Did you develop a feeling that money is evil or tainted? Or did you somehow get the feeling that YOU don’t deserve money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is such a taboo subject, and we all lay so much emotion on top of the concept of money, and receiving money can create such overwhelming emotions in us all. But we can overcome these feelings, and find a new, positive, relationship with money. 
First, it is important to remember, money in and of itself, is not positive OR negative. What we do with money can be of course. But the dollar in your hand is neutral. Also, money is not the goal. Money is a tool for making your life, and the lives of others better and more fulfilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;things-to-do&quot;&gt;Things to do&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can you do to counteract these old stories and patterns, and build a healthier relationship with receiving money? Here are some ideas. You don’t have to do all of them, and please feel free to modify these in a way that suits you and your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Become comfortable with talking about money. Talking about taboo subjects lessen their hold on us, and shine a light on what we’re really afraid of. Find someone safe, perhaps that has similar struggles with money, and become “Money Confidantes”. Make a regular coffee date, and take turns sharing your fears and concerns, then share your successes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a receiving ritual - Every time money comes into your hands, your bank account, or your PayPal account, ring a bell, light a candle, or say a prayer of thanks, or do all three. Or create another ritual that has meaning for you. Another fun way can be to say out loud: “Thank you &lt;person who=&quot;&quot; gave=&quot;&quot; you=&quot;&quot; the=&quot;&quot; money=&quot;&quot;&gt; for honoring me with this money. I honor you and the universe in return. I also honor myself, and I am grateful for the opportunity to receive this money”.&lt;/person&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend about five minutes a day visualizing what it will feel like to be wealthy and prosperous. Will you feel content for not having to worry daily about money? Do you feel joy for having the money you need to give back to people and causes you believe in? Do you feel grateful that you are protected in retirement, and will not need to depend on others as you age? When you imagine feeling wealthy, it helps you rewire your brain, and you will be more receptive to the money coming into your life right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;affirmations&quot;&gt;Affirmations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you can always work with affirmations. Here are some things to try saying to yourself every day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Money is not positive or negative. Money is a neutral. What I do with it is what brings value to it.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Having money, or not having money does not change my character. I am me, I am a beautiful sacred person, no matter how much money I have.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Money is not the goal. Money is a tool for making my life, and the lives of others, better and more fulfilling.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I am worthy of an abundant life. I do good works that are worth the reward of a fair payment”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I am so happy and grateful now that money comes to me in increasing quantities through multiple sources on a continuous basis.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you choose your affirmations, choose phrases that you can deeply believe. If you are not ready for an affirmation, or it is too “out there”, your subconscious will reject it. So if you need to modify any of these so they are believable to you, do that, and once you are comfortable with them, try expanding them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/05/02/Receiving-Money-Into-Your-Life.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/05/02/Receiving-Money-Into-Your-Life.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aging Your Money</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been so long since I have written on here! I’m glad to say, I’m back, and this will be the final post for the YNAB Series. So let’s get started on the last YNAB Rule!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html&quot;&gt;article “Make Your Budget Fit Your Life”&lt;/a&gt;, you’re beginning to see that the best budget is one that flexes with your life. We want a budget that works with us, rather then making us feel bad for not fitting into a rigid box. So what is the last rule? And what does it mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html&quot;&gt;What Are True Expenses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html&quot;&gt;Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html&quot;&gt;Aging Your Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, we’ve covered the three most fundamental rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give Every Dollar A Job&lt;/strong&gt;, which reminds us that we need to work with the reality of the dollars we have right now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embrace Your True Expenses&lt;/strong&gt;, which tells us that we need to account for every type of expense we have, not just your bills, and including your savings goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roll With The Punches&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives you permission to change your budget when you need to, and gives you a safe way to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;age-your-money&quot;&gt;Age Your Money&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last rule is “Age Your Money.” You can find the age of your money in the upper-right hand corner of the screen in YNAB:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/AgeOfMoney.png&quot; alt=&quot;Age Of Money Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aging Your Money means that we want to hold onto money for longer and longer periods of time. If you are living paycheck to paycheck, when you spend a dollar the day you got paid, that dollar is considered one day old. But if you hold onto that dollar until the next day, it will be two days old, and so on. So when we talk about aging your money, we are saying that we are living on dollars that we earned some time ago. And old money is good, because it means that we have savings, and are breaking out of the paycheck-to-paycheck cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth rule, incidentally, used to be “Live on Last Month’s Income”. With that rule, the goal was to age your money to at least 30 days old. So when you spent your money, it would have been money you earned last month. That was a pretty binary and rigid rule though, and it make it hard to see your progress, so now you can take it day by day, and increase the age of your money gradually, celebrating your progress as your money gets older. I still recommend setting 30 days as a good goal, though, because if you have 30 days, you’ve officially broken the paycheck-to-paycheck cycle, which is really an amazing accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that Aging Your Money is a fantastic goal. But I also think it is OK not to concentrate on it. You may put a high priority on paying down debt, or contributing to savings goals. By all means, feel free to ignore the number in the upper-right hand corner of your screen. If you are working the first three rules, the fourth rule will start to come to you naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it! The four YNAB rules, all there in black and white! All that is left is to &lt;a href=&quot;www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;Sign up for the one month YNAB Trial&lt;/a&gt;, or contact me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cecilia@bountifulmoneyllc.com&quot; target=&quot;&quot;&gt;cecilia@bountifulmoneyllc.com&lt;/a&gt; for more information and to set up an initial strategy session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Make Your Budget Fit Your Life</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html&quot;&gt;article last week&lt;/a&gt;, you know how to why it is important to embrace your true expenses, and what they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we know about Giving Every Dollar a Job, and Embracing our True Expenses, the next rule is Roll With the Punches, which is my favorite rule, because it is what transforms YNAB from an expense tracker to a guilt and shame free budget planner, and allows your budget to fit your life, instead of trying to fit your life to your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html&quot;&gt;What Are True Expenses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html&quot;&gt;Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html&quot;&gt;Aging Your Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it do that? Well, with the first two rules, we are creating our budget plan. We know we need to plan for every dollar (Rule 1) and we need to plan for every expenses (Rule 2). But what do we do when life doesn’t go according to plan? Do we throw out the plan? Or do we adjust the plan to work with our new situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course we work with our new situation. Most budgeting techniques tend to fall down on this part. You might make the most perfect plan at the start of the month, but if it isn’t easy to adjust the plan as you go along, you’ll find yourself gradually abandoning the plan. And you might even feel bad, like somehow you’re “bad at budgeting”. But that’s not true. Your budget is failing you, not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So YNAB has “Roll With the Punches”. Lets say your brother calls and says he’s unexpectedly going to be in town this weekend, could he come see you? Of course you want to have some fun with him, you don’t get to see him very often. So you plan to cook a nice dinner, and maybe you decide to surprise him with tickets to the local symphony. Maybe you have the money for the entertainment in your budget, but this special dinner is going to cost you $50 (you both sure like steak!), money that will take you over on your grocery budget. What should you do? You can just let the category go over $50, but that means that you can’t be sure you’ll have money available for your other categories (see the post on &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;envelope budgeting&lt;/a&gt; for more information). So we need to find that money from somewhere else in our budget. Maybe we reduce our savings on one of our savings categories, maybe Vacations or something like that. Or we might reduce the amount in one of our variable categories, like Entertainment, or Personal Care, or something like that. Wherever we might have money that you aren’t prioritizing as highly as this time with your brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is the key to Rolling With the Punches – What are your priorities &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? Do you want the manicure or the steak dinner more? Do you need to pay your electricity or save for emergencies? We make these choices all the time, but YNAB gives you a very clear way to see those choices, while making sure we don’t get into debt trying to do &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. There are no right or wrong answers to “what is my highest priority”? There’s only the answer that aligns most closely with your values and goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to leave you with one last thought about Rule 3. Sometimes when you’re just starting out, you might think the goal is to stop needing to Roll With the Punches. You &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to stop having to move things around due to poor decision-making, or emotional spending. But I’m here to tell you that I’ve been working with YNAB for four years, and I have used Rule 3 every single month I’ve used it. You want that flexibility to change our budget, because if it is inflexible, it won’t change with your changing circumstances, which means you may abandon your budget. Budgeting isn’t here to strangle you, or tell you what you “should” do. It’s here to help you prioritize your spending. And Rule 3 helps you do it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What are True Expenses?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;article last week&lt;/a&gt;, you know that you need to give your dollars jobs, but how do you decide what jobs are necessary in your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You use the second YNAB rule to figure that out. “Embrace Your True Expenses” tells us that we need to fully understand our expenses, and not just the regular bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html&quot;&gt;What Are True Expenses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html&quot;&gt;Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html&quot;&gt;Aging Your Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-true-expenses&quot;&gt;What are “true” expenses&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most folks have a pretty good idea of what their regular monthly expenses are. Keeping track of things like rent and utilities is usually pretty easy. But to budget fully, we really need to make sure we have a plan for everything we are going to spend money on. So what other kinds of expenses do we have that we need to give categories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think of expenses as four different kinds of expenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Frequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Infrequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Frequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Infrequent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “Regular” expense is one where you always know how much you are going to spend. “Irregular” means the amount can vary. “Frequent” means monthly, and “Infrequent” is less often then that. What are some examples of these expenses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Frequent - Your bills like rent, cell phone, and cable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Infrequent - Bills that happen every six months or a year, like car insurance premiums, or annual subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Frequent - Your bills like electricity (the amount varies from month to month) or expenses like groceries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Infrequent - Emergencies. If you own a car, I can guarantee you are going to have a car emergency, but I can’t predict when it will happen, or how much it will cost, so it belongs in this category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have accounted for your expenses in all four of these categories, you can say that you have “embraced your true expenses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-do-we-follow-this-rule&quot;&gt;Why do we follow this rule?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to follow this rule, because it allows us to smooth out our budget. If we know we have a car insurance premium payment coming up in five months for $300, we can start saving in that category now, so when the expense comes up we already have the money budgeted. Saving $60 per month is way easier then trying to come up with the full $300 in the moment, don’t you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps with our variable categories too, like groceries. We can start getting an idea of how much we really spend on groceries over time, and therefore we’ll get better at making guesses at how much we need to budget for it. That also helps us smooth out our budget over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, we can start saving for our emergencies. We know they are going to happen, so how much do we need to save into that category to feel secure? Making that decision depends entirely on how secure you want to feel in your situation. For your car emergency category, think about what makes sense. Do you have a brand new Toyota with a three year full warranty on it? Maybe you don’t need much in the category. Or do you have a twenty-year old jolopy? Maybe you would feel more comfortable with a large fund for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, one reason to have a budget is to reduce the surprises, and to smooth out your budget. Embracing Your True Expenses is the rule that helps us make that happen!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is the Purpose of Your Money?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What do you want your money to do for you? Do you want to travel the world with it, or buy a house for your family? What about taking art classes, or donating to causes you believe in? Is there something stopping you from achieving those goals? I know that for years, I never felt like I could save for those things, because I didn’t know if I had enough money. I didn’t know where my money was going, so I was afraid to use it for anything more then bills. If you are worried about covering your bills, then how can you set money aside for the bigger goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second article in the YNAB Series, and I’m going to talk about YNAB’s first rule – Give Every Dollar a Job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html&quot;&gt;What Are True Expenses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/02/07/Make-Your-Budget-Fit-Your-Life.html&quot;&gt;Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/04/26/Aging-Your-Money.html&quot;&gt;Aging Your Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main ways that budgeting helps us manage our money is by illuminating our money situation and our money habits. If we don’t know where we stand right now, and we don’t know our goals, we’ll never be able to plan how to get from the starting point to the end point. So the start of our budgeting practice is “Give Every Dollar a Job”. But what does that really mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, “Give Every Dollar a Job” implies that we are giving the money we have &lt;strong&gt;right now&lt;/strong&gt; jobs. By only working with money we currently have in our possession, we avoid “projecting” our budget. In many traditional budgeting systems, you start with the month by asking “OK, what money do I think I will get this month?” Even if you have a steady salary, that is a risky thing to do, because it roots your budget in a somewhat imaginary number. I think most of us know that in the back of our minds, and it undermines our confidence in our budget. Even more, when we budget money we don’t yet have, we can’t guarantee that when we spend from a category, that that money actually exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, giving every dollar a job means we are very intentional with our spending planning. We think through what we need to spend until the next time we get paid. When we put money into those categories, we can rest easy, knowing that the money will be ready when we need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, by giving every dollar a job we can trust our category balances. In other words, if I have all of my bill categories funded, if I go to the clothing store and look at my clothing category, and it says I have $100, that means I can spend up to $100 without having to worry if I’m somehow cutting into my rent money, or utilities, or anything else. All those categories are funded with real money, too, so spending money on clothing will have nothing to do with what you can spend later in those other categories. Again, the same as if I’m projecting my income, if I budget more dollars then I have, I can no longer trust my category balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-is-this-rule-so-important&quot;&gt;Why is this rule so important?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving Every Dollar A Job is the most fundamental method of &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;envelope budgeting&lt;/a&gt; – When you get money, you take all of that money and put it in envelopes. When you need that money, you take that envelope with you, and spend it. This is the same thing, but instead we’re using software, because it’s more flexible and fits into modern life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>