<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bountiful Money Coaching</title>
    <description>Save money, budget according to your values, and experience financial bliss</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>What are True Expenses?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve read the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html&quot;&gt;article last week&lt;/a&gt;, you know that you need to give your dollars jobs, but how do you decide what jobs are necessary in your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You use the second YNAB rule to figure that out. “Embrace Your True Expenses” tells us that we need to fully understand our expenses, and not just the regular bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming next) What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) What Are True Expenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Living on Last Month’s Income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-true-expenses&quot;&gt;What are “true” expenses&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most folks have a pretty good idea of what their regular monthly expenses are. Keeping track of things like rent and utilities is usually pretty easy. But to budget fully, we really need to make sure we have a plan for everything we are going to spend money on. So what other kinds of expenses do we have that we need to give categories?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think of expenses as four different kinds of expenses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Frequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Infrequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Frequent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Infrequent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “Regular” expense is one where you always know how much you are going to spend. “Irregular” means the amount can vary. “Frequent” means monthly, and “Infrequent” is less often then that. What are some examples of these expenses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Frequent - Your bills like rent, cell phone, and cable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular and Infrequent - Bills that happen every six months or a year, like car insurance premiums, or annual subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Frequent - Your bills like electricity (the amount varies from month to month) or expenses like groceries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irregular and Infrequent - Emergencies. If you own a car, I can guarantee you are going to have a car emergency, but I can’t predict when it will happen, or how much it will cost, so it belongs in this category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have accounted for your expenses in all four of these categories, you can say that you have “embraced your true expenses.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-do-we-follow-this-rule&quot;&gt;Why do we follow this rule?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to follow this rule, because it allows us to smooth out our budget. If we know we have a car insurance premium payment coming up in five months for $300, we can start saving in that category now, so when the expense comes up we already have the money budgeted. Saving $60 per month is way easier then trying to come up with the full $300 in the moment, don’t you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps with our variable categories too, like groceries. We can start getting an idea of how much we really spend on groceries over time, and therefore we’ll get better at making guesses at how much we need to budget for it. That also helps us smooth out our budget over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, we can start saving for our emergencies. We know they are going to happen, so how much do we need to save into that category to feel secure? Making that decision depends entirely on how secure you want to feel in your situation. For your car emergency category, think about what makes sense. Do you have a brand new Toyota with a three year full warranty on it? Maybe you don’t need much in the category. Or do you have a twenty-year old jolopy? Maybe you would feel more comfortable with a large fund for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, one reason to have a budget is to reduce the surprises, and to smooth out your budget. Embracing Your True Expenses is the rule that helps us make that happen!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/31/What-Are-True-Expenses.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is the Purpose of Your Money?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What do you want your money to do for you? Do you want to travel the world with it, or buy a house for your family? What about taking art classes, or donating to causes you believe in? Is there something stopping you from achieving those goals? I know that for years, I never felt like I could save for those things, because I didn’t know if I had enough money. I didn’t know where my money was going, so I was afraid to use it for anything more then bills. If you are worried about covering your bills, then how can you set money aside for the bigger goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second article in the YNAB Series, and I’m going to talk about YNAB’s first rule – Give Every Dollar a Job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming next) What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) What Are True Expenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Living on Last Month’s Income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main ways that budgeting helps us manage our money is by illuminating our money situation and our money habits. If we don’t know where we stand right now, and we don’t know our goals, we’ll never be able to plan how to get from the starting point to the end point. So the start of our budgeting practice is “Give Every Dollar a Job”. But what does that really mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, “Give Every Dollar a Job” implies that we are giving the money we have &lt;strong&gt;right now&lt;/strong&gt; jobs. By only working with money we currently have in our possession, we avoid “projecting” our budget. In many traditional budgeting systems, you start with the month by asking “OK, what money do I think I will get this month?” Even if you have a steady salary, that is a risky thing to do, because it roots your budget in a somewhat imaginary number. I think most of us know that in the back of our minds, and it undermines our confidence in our budget. Even more, when we budget money we don’t yet have, we can’t guarantee that when we spend from a category, that that money actually exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, giving every dollar a job means we are very intentional with our spending planning. We think through what we need to spend until the next time we get paid. When we put money into those categories, we can rest easy, knowing that the money will be ready when we need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, by giving every dollar a job we can trust our category balances. In other words, if I have all of my bill categories funded, if I go to the clothing store and look at my clothing category, and it says I have $100, that means I can spend up to $100 without having to worry if I’m somehow cutting into my rent money, or utilities, or anything else. All those categories are funded with real money, too, so spending money on clothing will have nothing to do with what you can spend later in those other categories. Again, the same as if I’m projecting my income, if I budget more dollars then I have, I can no longer trust my category balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-is-this-rule-so-important&quot;&gt;Why is this rule so important?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving Every Dollar A Job is the most fundamental method of &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;envelope budgeting&lt;/a&gt; – When you get money, you take all of that money and put it in envelopes. When you need that money, you take that envelope with you, and spend it. This is the same thing, but instead we’re using software, because it’s more flexible and fits into modern life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/24/Give-Every-Dollar-A-Job.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>YNAB - My budgeting software of choice</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Budgeting is the foundation of building a wonderful and stable financial life. But I don’t like the way budgeting is usually taught, when it is taught at all. Forecasting and rigidity are common problems that you may have encountered in trying to budget. &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;Envelope Budgeting&lt;/a&gt; is something I have recommended before, and I mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;YNAB (You Need A Budget)&lt;/a&gt; as my software of choice to implement envelope budgeting. Let’s dig into YNAB, see what it can give us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest of the series here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html&quot;&gt;What is YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming next) What is the Purpose of Your Money?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) What Are True Expenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Make Your Budget Fit Your Life (not the other way around)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Coming up) Living on Last Month’s Income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-ynab&quot;&gt;Why YNAB?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used YNAB personally for over three years, and in that time, I’ve completely turned around my life. We paid off my and my husband’s student loans, car loans, paid off our credit cards, and have stopped using them as a crutch. I credit that in large part to how YNAB works. In a nutshell, YNAB is a philosophy that is supported by software. There are four “rules”, more like guidelines, that the software helps you follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-four-ynab-rules&quot;&gt;The four YNAB rules&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four rules are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give Every Dollar a Job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embrace Your True Expenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roll With The Punches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live on Last Month’s Income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you work with these rules, you will find your financial life starts making sense, and you can start spending according to your values and goals, because you will have clarity on your &lt;strong&gt;whole&lt;/strong&gt; situation. I will go through all four of these rules in brief here, but I plan on writing articles on each of the rules in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;give-every-dollar-a-job&quot;&gt;Give Every Dollar a Job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fundamental rule is why YNAB is an envelope budgeting system. Every time you receive money, you give it a job, which in YNAB you do by putting the money in categories you have set up. These categories are like the envelopes you would use if you were working in a cash system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to give every dollar a job, because then everything has a purpose. When you allocate $300 for groceries, you know what the purpose is for that $300. Also it keeps you from allocating more then one job for your dollars. If, for example, you have your $1200 rent payment in the rent category, you know you can pay it without worrying about it affecting your grocery category. It is extremely powerful to be able to spend from a category without having to worry that your other plans will get affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embrace-your-true-expenses&quot;&gt;Embrace Your True Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had a bill come up that comes up every six months, and been surprised by it? Maybe you even had to tighten your belt on other expenses to be able to pay for it? Or had an unexpected car breakdown that completely wrecked your finances for months? With YNAB, you can make room for all your expenses, whether they be frequent and a regular amount, or infrequent and a surprising amount. You can break down those expenses to smaller monthly chunks that will have a much smaller affect on your budget, and you’ll be ready for any kind of expense you may have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roll-with-the-punches&quot;&gt;Roll with the Punches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tell my clients, this is my favorite rule! This is truly what sets YNAB apart from other programs for me. This rule means that when your life or your priorities change, your budget changes with it, instead of &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/12/27/Guilt-And-Shame.html&quot;&gt;shaming&lt;/a&gt; you for not “sticking to your budget”. When you have something unexpected happen, and you need to spend more in a category, that’s just fine! Just find the money in other categories and move it to the category that needed it. No guilt, no shame, just your budget moving with you&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;live-on-last-months-income&quot;&gt;Live on Last Month’s Income&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living on Last Month’s Income means that when you start a new month, you have all the money you need to fully budget that month. It means that you are always working one month ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would we do this? It does a couple things. One is it simplifies monthly budgeting. Instead of budgeting every time you get paid, you can budget all at once, on the first of the month. Second, it means you don’t have to “time” your bills. Because all bills are given a job on the first of the month, you can conceivably pay any bill at any time in the month. In fact, you could pay them all on the first, if you wanted to. These two main things lead to one amazing thing - it reduces financial stress. Can you imagine not worrying about your bills and when they are paid? It is an amazing feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of Living on Last Month’s Income is that you have an automatic one-month emergency fund. If, for example, you lose your job, you have a full month breathing space to strategize, and work to get a new job. And when you look for a job with less stress, you will do a better job interviewing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to sign up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;YNAB&lt;/a&gt;. You can try it for 34 days free, and thereafter it is $6.99/mo, billed annually. I also provide local and remote &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/services.html&quot;&gt;Money Coaching&lt;/a&gt;, to help you align your money habits with your values and goals. And stay tuned for my articles expanding on YNAB’s Four Rules!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/17/YNAB.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My yearly review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned last week, I’m not big on New Year Resolutions. But I do think it is important to make goals, and track our progress. The past few years, I’ve done an informal, high level yearly review of my financial situation, and it’s really helped me gain a perspective of how my goals change over time. I’d like to share with you my 2017 review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this list down at the beginning of last year, in a calendar item set for the beginning of this January. Notice how high level it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kill the boat loan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move onto boat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move to remote job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully Fund Roth IRA’s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maximize 401(k)s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a retirement portfolio worth of more than $340,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this list compare to where I stand right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kill-the-boat-loan-and-move-onto-the-boat&quot;&gt;Kill the boat loan, and move onto the boat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DONE! I’m going to combine these two goals into one, because they are related in how I achieved them. I did this one by selling my house, moving onto the boat, and using some of the proceeds to pay off the remainder of the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;move-to-remote-job&quot;&gt;Move to remote job&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SORT OF. I quit my job, and am working at building my own business (Money Coaching, FTW!). Much of this work can be done at home. It has the added advantage of being very flexible, and it’s empowering to work for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fully-fund-roth-iras&quot;&gt;Fully Fund Roth IRA’s&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DONE! Even though I don’t have a job anymore, I had a job for half the year, which means I can fund my Roth. I may need to figure out a different retirement vehicle for next year, if I continue to not have a traditional job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;maximize-my-401k&quot;&gt;Maximize my 401(k)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SORT OF. I maxed it for some of the year, but when I realized the coming changes in my life, I reduced it to the percentage that my company made contributions for. When I quit my job, even that went away. But I’m going to count this one as a success, because I did the right things at the right time. Remember, don’t be a slave to your goals, just for the sake of checking them off! Do what is important is to do what is right for your life, at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-a-retirement-portfolio-worth-of-more-than-340000&quot;&gt;Have a retirement portfolio worth of more than $340,000&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DONE! I set this goal when I was looking at my retirement situation from a combined perspective. When my husband and I separated (see below), I think this goal needs to be separated, too. That makes my goal $170,000. I hit over $250,000 this year, so I’ve definitely surpassed it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-else-happened-this-year&quot;&gt;What else happened this year?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I separated from my husband of 15 years, and we’re on track to get divorced early this year. We’ve both made it personal goals to stay good friends, and so far, I feel we’ve done very well at that. While this isn’t a financial goal, it has wide-ranging ramifications on all of my financial goals, so I included it anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I quit my job. This one is &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; for me. I loved my job and I had been at the company over five years. I loved the people I worked with, and enjoyed the kind of work I did. But over the last year and a half or so, the company had been making increasingly poor decisions. Several people I enjoyed working with either moved on, or were laid off. And worst of all, the environment turned toxic. I ended up having a terrible panic attack, directly related to the job. I’ve never seen such a fast change in attitudes. I was quite frankly appalled at the way people were treated, and finally couldn’t stomach staying there another day, especially as it was affecting my mental health. I took the leap, and I haven’t looked back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I turned in a leased car, thus eliminating that lease, and I bought a car with cash. It’s a simple older Toyota Yaris, but its mine, and I never owed anyone for it!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am now &lt;strong&gt;completely&lt;/strong&gt; debt free! I am my own woman, and not beholden to anyone else. Except my cat. I’m always beholden to her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-conclusions-can-i-draw-from-this-review&quot;&gt;What conclusions can I draw from this review?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s always interesting to me to see how far off my life is from what I imagined, even over the course of only one year. I got a divorce, which sent me scrambling for security in my personal life, even while I used it as an opportunity to take a huge chance in my professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-my-goals-for-2018&quot;&gt;What are my goals for 2018?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I think I’ve learned a lot over this past year. My retirement goals are still very important to me, but I’ve been easing off on them a bit in order to concentrate on shifting my career. It’s become more important to me to contribute to the world around me in some beneficial way, and I think that coaching people to improve their financial health is a very good contribution to the world. I haven’t put my other goals completely aside, but I have to concentrate on other things right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is my list for 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be making enough money with my own business to sustain myself at my &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html&quot;&gt;Bare Bones Number&lt;/a&gt;. Right now that is about $2800/mo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And if I haven’t achieved that, have a part-time in a related field to continue growing and expanding professionally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay debt-free!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contribute to my retirement funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a retirement portfolio worth $275,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-about-you&quot;&gt;What about you?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does your 2017 review look like? And what goals have you set for 2018?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/10/Yearly-review.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/10/Yearly-review.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Happy New Year! Welcome to the new year of financial bliss!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to 2018! I am so excited for the new year! 2017 was a year filled with changes for me, and I am excited to see what comes to fruition and what still needs work. I am not one for New Year’s Resolutions, but I know they can be very helpful to motivate people to &lt;strong&gt;get started&lt;/strong&gt; with something great. Getting started is often the hardest part of any worthy endeavor. Do you have any resolutions related to money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you want to get out of debt, or increase your savings? Or perhaps you want to start saving for a down payment, or buy a car with cash for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your goals, I can help you get started! The foundation to achieving your money goals is creating a budget that works with your life, your values, and your goals. Please contact me if you would like guided and personalized coaching to help you achieve your goals in 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/03/Happy-New-Year.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2018/01/03/Happy-New-Year.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Guilt and Shame</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you feel guilty about your money past? Perhaps you’ve made a bad investment, or haven’t invested at all. Maybe you trusted someone stole money from you, or you have a spending addiction. Whatever it is, we all have times that we have made bad decisions involving money, and that can lead to all sorts of negative emotions – guilt, anger, betrayal, shame, and more. What’s worse, over time it can leave you feeling in doubt of your own ability to manage money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-family-history-with-money&quot;&gt;My family history with money&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not alone! Most people have a bad story involving money. My personal story is actually rather average. My father made pretty good money all throughout my childhood, but neither of my parents were really good at managing money, so all through my childhood, even though we were middle class, it always felt like we were one disaster away from total financial devastation. That fostered a lasting feeling of insecurity that I have spent most of my adult life trying to create a perfectly secure environment around me. In the small things, I’m spontaneous (friends might call me “random”), but in the large things I am &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; conservative. I started saving for retirement early by saving into my very first 401(k) and starting a Roth IRA as soon as I had my first job. Investing may seem very risky to many people, but I saw it as a way to make sure that I never ended up depending on a by-no-means guaranteed social security check in my old age. I knew that if I invested early in relatively risky stocks, I would have time to recover from market downturns, and reap the rewards of time spent invested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all may seem fine, but I did it to the exclusion of other parts of my life. I was so scared of losing that ability to save, that I stayed in jobs long after they had ceased to be a challenge, or made me happy. I stayed in personal relationships because they were a good bet financially (well, it’s never that simple, but it was certainly a factor). So my life got pretty far out of balance for a lot of years. I’ve made changes to try to counteract it, but like many things, it’s a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I do feel guilty. I also feel sad, like I lost so many years being scared. And a bit angry at myself for not being more true to myself. I acknowledge those feelings, but I also am working to change my world as it is right now. That is most important. I think I will always struggle with finding the balance of too stodgy and too reckless. But the most important thing is that I’m aware, and I’m always trying to find the balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-reasons-we-may-feel-guilt-and-shame&quot;&gt;Other reasons we may feel guilt and shame&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may, like me, feel guilty because of behaviors you learned from your family history. But there are other reasons, too. Some of them are cultural. Perhaps you are a woman, and have been told in countless small and large ways that you can’t possibly be good with money. Or maybe the cultural stigma of not talking about money has made it hard for you to seek help when you were confused about your money situation. There are many ways our own culture and society can undermine our relationships with money, and what’s worse, they can be hard to identify, because we’re so steeped in our own cultural biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps you have had one or many bad experiences with money personally. Perhaps a bad investment, or getting out of the market at the wrong time made you lose a lot of money, and your confidence was lost at the same time. Or you’ve always been a shop-a-holic, and you know how much that has damaged your financial security. Whatever it is, you can absolutely have negative feelings that undermine your ability to get back to a healthy, trusting relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-should-we-do-about-our-guilt-and-shame&quot;&gt;What should we do about our guilt and shame?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first want to make sure that you honor your feelings. So often, we push away our negative feelings, because they are unpleasant. But to truly savor the joys in life, it is necessary to be fully present when we are experiencing the negative. So before you do anything else, spend a few moments just sitting with your feelings. What are those feelings? When you contemplate them, do other feelings wash over you, too? Or maybe memories come back to you? Sometimes it is helpful to journal this experience. You may find that journaling (like the &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/15/The-Five-Whys.html&quot;&gt;Five Whys&lt;/a&gt; exercise) helps you dig deeper into your past experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to feel your feelings, but you can then harness them to make positive changes in your life. I like to reframe my negative emotions about money – they are trying to send up a red flag that your finances are not in balance with your values. If you see the red flags, you can change your behaviors. Once you have acknowledged and honored your feelings, you can get down to the business of figuring out how to modify your behaviors. Remember, even small changes can make a huge difference in your life overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your negative feelings about money can be a natural consequence of your cultural, familial, and personal experiences with money. You are not alone in feeling guilt and shame about our money situation, most of us have had negative experiences in the past with money. The great thing is, they are important red flags that can help you recognize what you want to change in your life. And once you start making changes in your life that align your finances with your values, you will find yourself healing your relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/27/Guilt-And-Shame.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/27/Guilt-And-Shame.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What To Do When Your Expenses are more than your Income!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So you’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html&quot;&gt;Calculated your Bare Bones Number&lt;/a&gt; and you know that your expenses are larger than your income. What do you do now? The first thing is, pause and honor yourself taking an open-eyed look at your situation. You can’t fix an issue if you don’t even know it exists, so congratulate yourself for understanding where you stand right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, how much is the difference between your income and your squeak-by expenses? Is it a few dollars, is it hundreds, or even thousands of dollars more per month? Knowing how drastic the difference is will tell you how drastic your action will need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How have you been dealing with this discrepancy in your life up until now? Are you racking up debt, draining your savings, living off of others? Whatever it is, it’s important to understand how it has been affecting your life so far, and how you cope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are asking yourself these questions, remember to pay attention to your emotions. Dealing with a situation like this can be distressing, and you want to make sure that you don’t become so distraught that you abandon this exploration, and go bury your head in the sand. Any time you start feeling angry, guilty or ashamed, do something calming. Make yourself a cup of tea, stand up and stretch, call a supportive friend, whatever you need to do to get your stress levels down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have an idea of how big the difference between your income and expenses is, you can start strategizing on how you will solve it. Here is the basic rule – If your expenses are bigger than your income, you will be doing one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decrease your expenses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase your income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draw from your savings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get into more debt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those choices are the only choices you have, when you have more expenses than income. Notice the order I put them in - They are roughly in order of most ideal to least ideal. You should try to do one or both of the first two &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; you resort to one of the last two. It may seem obvious, but how often have you reached for your credit card, before even thinking about the other options you may have? That said, sometimes your situation is dire enough that you will need to use your savings or create more debt. Perhaps you are recently unemployed. When that is the case, you will be working on increasing your income by trying to get a new job, but in the meantime, you will have to draw from your savings if you have it, or go into debt if you don’t. Drawing from savings is obviously better in that situation, but if you don’t have savings, then debt is going to be your last resort. I’ll talk in later articles about how to save money for emergencies like unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even when you are using your savings or increasing debt, you will want to concentrate on one or both of the first two, so you can stop using your savings as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets examine the pros and cons of both:
Decreasing expenses can be much faster than increasing your income. Increasing income usually means getting a higher paying job, getting a raise, starting a second job, or starting a side-hustle. That can take a while to get, plus then even after you get it, you may need to wait for two weeks or a month to get your first paycheck or invoice paid. Even selling things you own can take time, you need to list it, then someone needs to see it, etcetera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decreasing expenses often entails cancelling a service online, or a simple phone call to a service company, which can be relatively quick. There are many articles out there for techniques on doing things like lowering your phone bill, so I won’t go over them here, but I highly suggest googling them. People have been very resourceful over time, and it can be inspiring to see what others do to decrease expenses without decreasing their lifestyle much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing income may be slower, but it can have a much bigger impact on that delta between expenses and income. After all, you may save $80/month on cable, but a raise or better job may be ten times that much, depending on many factors. It takes a while, but can have a real impact on your financial life. Also, you may already be operating with your expenses very close to the bone. In that case, you may not have much on the expenses side that you can cut. But just a gentle reminder, often you can cut more than you think. We as humans get used to a certain level of expenses in our lives, and they can start to seem necessary, even when they really aren’t. Try to take a level look at your expenses, are they &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; necessary? And are they necessary, &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? Could you cut them out for a while, as you get yourself back on your feet? Not all expenses have to be cut forever. But you may find that some of those expenses you never let back into your life, because it turns out you do just fine without them! I’ve personally never regretted cancelling cable, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quick-review&quot;&gt;Quick Review&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Decrease Expenses&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Increase Income&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Can be much faster&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Can have a larger effect on your budget&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;May not be able to reduce very much&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Can take a really long time&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t have a discrepancy between your income and your Squeak-By Expenses, you may have one between your income and your average spending. You may want to go through this process in that situation too, because the same risks exist, like getting yourself into more debt, creating instability in your life, and so on. The only difference is, while you are figuring it out, you should be able to reduce your expenses to the Bare Bones level while you work through how you want to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/20/More-Expenses-Then-Income.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/20/More-Expenses-Then-Income.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Is Your Bare Bones Number?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you know what financial level you are living at? Are you living close to the bone, or are you living freely, with all of your needs &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; your wants being met? And how do you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When clients come to me to get their finances under control, one of the first things I do is help them to understand their “Bare Bones Number.” My mentor &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lunajaffe.com&quot;&gt;Luna Jaffe&lt;/a&gt; likes to call it the “Squeak-By Number,” because it’s the number that you would be just squeaking by on. It is the minimum amount of money you could spend every month, to just barely get by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to know your Bare Bones Number, because then you are aware of how much you could cut from your life in an emergency, if absolutely everything went wrong, what would you be left paying? And it is very useful to have this as a calculated number, because it gives a sense of peace and control to know what you could cut down to, and still live. It also shows you whether you are already living Bare-Bones or not. A lot of folks think they are living at the absolute edge of their expenses, but we often find that there are still places that you can cut expenses, sometimes with little to no effect on your  quality of life. We get so used to the amenities and experiences in our lives, sometimes it ends up feeling like those are necessities, when in reality, they don’t really belong below the Bare-Bones line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-exercise&quot;&gt;The exercise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take out a piece of paper (or a spreadsheet, if that’s what you like), then go through all of your bank statements for ALL of your personal accounts including your credit cards, for the last two months. For every charge decide, ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Was this necessary for my most basic living?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things are easy. Your utility bills are one that is obviously Bare-Bones. Also minimum debt payments are another. You &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; keep up with your debt payments, because the consequences of not doing so can be dire. Things like rent, though, are deceptive. It seems Bare Bones, but is it really? Are you living in the smallest house or apartment you could be? Would it be possible for you to move somewhere cheaper, and still be happy and comfortable? We Americans live in &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; houses, maybe a smaller apartment wouldn’t be as much fun, but it may serve your Bare Bones Number little better. The same goes with groceries. Bare Bones doesn’t mean organic. It means the cheapest you can get away with and still be relatively healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you go through your statements, write down the items that you decide are Bare Bones on your paper, and write down how much you spent in one month for that item. When you are done, you should have a list of items that you can total up. That total is your Bare Bones Number. Now ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How does this number make me feel?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it seem too high? Is it too low? How close is your current living situation to your Bare Bones number? This exercise can bring up all sorts of emotions. Perhaps you are distressed at how high the number is, or how close it is to your current living situation. Or maybe you have realized that you can live on even less than you ever thought you could. What a feeling of freedom, knowing you can cut way back, and still survive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one will have the same Bare Bones number. We all live different lives. Perhaps you have medical issues that others don’t, or you have kids. Or you live in an expensive city. All these things can effect that number, so it’s not helpful to compare your number with other people’s. But what can be helpful is revisiting this number over time, every six months or so. Our own lives change all the time, so your number will probably change, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-can-you-use-this-number&quot;&gt;How can you use this number?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not advocating you make it a goal to live at your Bare Bones Number. It is actually the opposite. Once you know what your Bare Bones Number is, and if your income is significantly over that, then of course you can add in the things that make our lives full and rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are living well, and have a good job, just knowing your number can help you understand how much you need to save for an emergency fund. Many people advise having at least 6 months of expenses saved. Now you can take your Bare Bones Number, multiply by six, and know how much is a fairly good Emergency Fund goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are already living close to your Bare Bones Number, this exercises often brings up areas where you can cut even further. If you cut just a bit more, you might be able to buy yourself some breathing room, while you use other methods to also improve your financial situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you may find in calculating your Bare Bones Number that your expenses are larger than your income. My next article will be about what to do if you find yourself in that situation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/13/Bare-Bones-Number.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Credit Card Float</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a hidden debt trap that you could be falling into. I know I sound like one of those terrible commercials trying to persuade you to give them money to get your debt cancelled. But there &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; a way to get into debt without knowing you are in debt, and it is called “Credit Card Float.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credit Card Float is where you charge your everyday expenses to your credit card over the period of the month, then when you get paid, you pay off the credit card in full, thus never incurring any interest payments. The trouble is, you don’t have enough money to pay for your upcoming expenses, so you have to turn right around and start using the credit card again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the simple way to tell if you are Floating. Ask yourself “If I paid off my credit card today, would I have enough money to cover my expenses until the next time I get paid?” If you answer no, then you are Floating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are in debt because you are paying for expenses first, then getting your income to cover those expenses later. It means that if for some reason you became unemployed, or stopped making money, you would already be one month of expenses in debt, with no way to pay it off. What a scary place to be! Just when you need full reserves, you’ll find yourself in debt before you can even think about how to get out of your current income crunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ynab.com&quot;&gt;YNAB&lt;/a&gt;, my favorite budgeting program, one of the four rules used to be “Live on Last Month’s Income”. I will write about that rule sometime in the future, but basically the idea is you are always running one month ahead of your expenses. When you are Floating, you are doing the opposite, you are paying for today’s expenses with &lt;strong&gt;next&lt;/strong&gt; month’s income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-you-get-out-of-credit-card-float&quot;&gt;How do you get out of Credit Card Float?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to get out of the Credit Card Float. But here are a few ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stop&quot;&gt;Stop!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above all, stop using your credit card, and start using your debit card. This separates your ongoing spending from your Float (debt), which makes it easier to use any one of the following methods to pay off the Float. Note that when you switch to the debit card, you will not be able to pay off your credit card in full next month, because you were using that money to pay this month’s expenses, which will mean you will start incurring interest charges. Usually Float isn’t a huge amount, as it is equal to one month’s expenses, so if you prioritize paying of your Float, you’ll be able to get rid of it quickly, and probably have spent very little on interest in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to keep paying at least the minimum payment, though! You don’t want to harm your credit while you’re paying down this debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-your-savings&quot;&gt;Use your savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky enough to have some savings, you can pull some of those savings out, and pay off your credit card bill with that, instead of next month’s paycheck. This is probably the quickest and cheapest way to get current with your credit card. It can hurt emotionally to use your savings to pay the Float, but remember, your savings is already a bit illusory, because you are also in debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;throw-your-extra-cash-into-it&quot;&gt;Throw your extra cash into it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a windfall, sell something, or get a gift, throw that money at your credit card. Every little bit helps, and eventually, you will pay off your Float.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-your-extra-paycheck&quot;&gt;Use your extra paycheck.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you get paid every two weeks? If so, every year you have two months where you get paid three times a month, instead of two. If one of those months is coming up, consider using the “extra” paycheck to throw at your Float. It can bring your balance down by at least half, which is a huge morale boost, then you can work on the rest of the balance using other methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few ideas for paying it down. Like all debt payment strategies, the most important thing is to get creative! Make it a game – how quickly can you pay down your Float?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve paid off your Float, you can consider starting to use your credit card again. Because you already have a proven track record of paying your credit card off every month, you’ll probably continue to do well with it. But now when you use it, every dollar you spend on your credit card, you know you have a dollar in your bank account that backs that debt. It’s an amazing feeling to know that you can pay your credit card at any time, and still have enough money in your account to pay for all your expenses!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/06/Credit-Card-Float.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/12/06/Credit-Card-Float.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Balance Giving with Budgeting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When we explore our money life, we dig deep into our bills, essentials like groceries, debt payments, and discretionary spending. But today I’d like to focus on one kind of spending that can cause a wide range of emotional reactions, especially during the holiday season: Giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving needs to be explored at a personal finance level because generosity is an important aspect of most people’s lives. I have found in my time as a Money Coach, there are clients that are willing to reduce expenses in a wide variety of areas in their lives, but will flat out refuse to eliminate or reduce their giving. And I understand that! Giving can be tied into who we are as people. We identify with the causes we give to, and it can feel miserly to stop or reduce giving. So let’s examine how giving can fit into our life, now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-personal-history-with-giving&quot;&gt;My personal history with giving&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently took a class from my mentor Luna Jaffe called &lt;a href=&quot;http://lunajaffe.com/wild-money/&quot;&gt;Wild Money&lt;/a&gt;. In this class she talked about six different aspects of personal finance: Receiving, Spending, Nurturing, Growing, Protecting, and Giving. I struggled more with the Giving section than I did with the other five sections &lt;strong&gt;combined&lt;/strong&gt;. I had some angry reactions to talking about generosity and giving. That in turn made me feel guilty and like I was a bad person. It turns out I’m and under-giver (more on under- and over-giving later) which means I don’t give as much as my life situation could allow, and I don’t give as much as I would like to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is that? In the Wild Money class, we explored various reasons why I could be struggling so much with giving. Not until the very end of class did I realize that I have a couple of deep family dynamics that have conspired to make giving a difficult subject. My mother was, towards the end of her life, a very needy person. She would take from me, emotionally and financially, without regard for my ability to give, and I finally had to put some very firm boundaries between her and me in order to maintain my sanity. This led me to have some pretty complex feelings about what it means to give to people, especially those that need a lot of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another dynamic I discovered is my family has a history of strings-attached giving. Again, this makes it hard for me to understand how a healthy, freely given gift looks and works. I have by no means fully worked through these issues, but just knowing they exist makes me realize I’m not just a bad person for my under-giving behaviors. And it gives me a basis to heal my relationship with giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself, how was giving modeled in your family? Have you had times where giving was not healthy in your life? Do you connect giving with manipulation, as I do? Or does it stem from guilt or other negative feelings? Understanding your history can help you progress to a healthy relationship with giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-in-balance&quot;&gt;Giving in balance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you continue to give, while healing your own financial situation? Like many things, I ascribe to the mantra of &lt;em&gt;balance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, let’s say you work for a non-profit, collecting donations for a cause you believe in. Every month, a woman comes in, and writes you a check for $500 dollars. It’s a generous gift, and you are always delighted to see her. One day, you notice she’s outside, arguing with a younger man, who walks away as she comes inside. As she opens her checkbook, she says, “my son is always trying to tell me what to do. He says I’m getting myself into debt because of this. But I don’t care, this cause is too important to stop.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would this make you feel? Would you feel good that she is overextending herself in order to give to your cause? Or would you be sad that she is spending beyond her means, causing her and her family distress and strife?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably would want her to stop overextending herself, even though you yourself believe so strongly in your cause. Turn that back on yourself – do you give so much of yourself that you have nothing left for yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-from-abundance&quot;&gt;Giving from abundance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually only recommend reducing your giving spending when your life is particularly out of balance: you either have far too little income to support your giving, or your giving is causing you to go into debt. You may have objections to reducing giving spending, but I want you to consider two things. The first is that this is only a temporary measure. The second is that we want to reduce your spending now so you can get your situation stable, so that you can spend more on giving later. When you are able to give from a place of abundance, you can give freely, and the gifts can do more good than if you are giving from a place of scarcity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;giving-creatively&quot;&gt;Giving creatively&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, if you need to reduce your giving, what should you do? You can continue to give while you are financially stretched, but it must be done creatively. You can give in various ways, but the two most common are: giving money, and giving time. If you are reducing your spending, then volunteering your time can be a rewarding way of giving of yourself. In fact, you may find that you like the hands-on nature of giving like this. You can dig into the details of causes that interest you, and find real reward by giving your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-kind-of-giver-are-you&quot;&gt;What Kind of Giver Are You?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-give-beyond-your-means&quot;&gt;You give beyond your means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you give beyond your means, it makes it harder to take care of yourself, which means it is going to be harder to give to others later. It can be difficult (or impossible!) for you to say no when someone needs something, even if you have nothing to give. Giving beyond your means will cause a sort of burnout, and can even lead to debt and other financial distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-give-less-than-your-means&quot;&gt;You give less than your means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you give less than your means, you are giving less than you could afford to, and more importantly you give less than your values would normally lead you to. It can cause anxiety and guilt, because you may know you aren’t spending your money according to your values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-people-give-out-of-balance-with-their-situation&quot;&gt;Why do people give out of balance with their situation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be many reasons why people give out of balance from their means. Both over- and under-giving can be because of self-esteem issues: You don’t feel you have anything of worth to give, or perhaps you don’t feel &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; are worth taking care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving out of balance can also be because they are unclear in their financial situation. Or perhaps you so overwhelmed by the needs of the world, you shut down, and don’t give to anyone.
Remember, giving to yourself is giving too! Taking care of yourself helps those around you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding why you give out of balance to your means can help you understand how to change your situation. Listen to your heart! How can you best &lt;strong&gt;give&lt;/strong&gt; of yourself, after you have done enough to &lt;strong&gt;take care&lt;/strong&gt; of yourself first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-one-week-exercise&quot;&gt;A One Week Exercise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-give-more-than-your-means&quot;&gt;If you give more than your means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a powerful exercises I learned from the Wild Money course. For one week, put yourself on a “giving fast”. Do not give money to anyone or anything. Every time you would normally give but don’t, write it down. Write down to whom, how much, and how it made you feel to not give that money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week, you may be surprised by how you feel. One client told me she felt valuable and powerful. She started recognizing things she gives for that actually aren’t very well aligned to her values, because she didn’t have as strong an emotional reaction to not giving in those situations. Other things were clearly more aligned because it was quite painful to not give to them. At the end of the week, she went back to giving for those things she felt strongly about, and stopped the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another client noticed that she had to not help a friend out that she normally would have immediately given money to. She instead supported her friend emotionally as she looked for another way. As she watched this friend, she noticed she seemed to feel empowered that she had earned the money herself, instead of relying on a friend. The real gift was to allow her friend to work and grow on her own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-give-less-than-your-means&quot;&gt;If you give less than your means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one week, commit to giving an amount of money every day. Give it to someone in need, like a homeless person, or to someone that it may delight. You can give a larger tip, or give to a charity. Whatever strikes your fancy that day. It could be $10, $20 or $50 a day. Whatever makes sense in your current financial situation. Every time you give that money away, write it down. Write who you gave it to, and how it made you feel to give the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find that giving regularly like this may bring up strong emotions, like it did for me. Whatever they are, write them down, and explore them further. They are probably trying to tell you something, maybe about your past, maybe about a misalignment between your behavior and your values. Whatever it is, try to follow it fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting into the habit of giving can open up a world of gratitude. You can start seeing the world in terms of how you can help. You have value that can help others! What a powerful feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;at-the-end-of-the-week&quot;&gt;At the end of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of this exercise, look over what you wrote, and remember how you felt. Did you run into problems or strong emotions? Did you go back to your usual habits halfway through? Or did you feel content and happy? Whatever it was remember it and write it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing you can do is plan for her giving in your budget. Budgeting (especially &lt;a href=&quot;/post/2017/11/22/Envelope-Budgeting.html&quot;&gt;Envelope Budgeting&lt;/a&gt;) will allow you to find a balance that will allow for sustained giving over the rest of your life. It can help you understand whether your are giving within your means and in balance with your life, and can help you understand whether your are giving according to your values. It can also help you see how your increasing financial stability can help you be a more generous and giving person, without neglecting your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/29/How-To-Balance-Giving-With-Budgeting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//post/2017/11/29/How-To-Balance-Giving-With-Budgeting.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>